{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Harsha stopped the use of animal food throughout his empire ",
            "optionB": "  Harsha erected thousands of stupas ",
            "optionC": "  Harsha regularly held the quinquennial convocation ",
            "optionD": "  Harsha sent missionaries to the west to propagate Buddhism ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarsha became a devout Buddhist at some point in his life. Xuanzang states that Harsha banned animal slaughter for food, and built monasteries at the places visited by Gautama Buddha. He erected several thousand 100-feet high stupas on the banks of the Ganges river, and built well-maintained hospices for travelers and poor people on highways across India. He organized an annual assembly of global scholars, and bestowed charitable alms on them. Every five years, he held a great assembly called Moksha. Xuanzang also describes a 21-day religious festival organized by Harsha in Kannauj; during this festival, Harsha and his subordinate kings performed daily rituals before a life-sized golden statue of the Buddha. ",
            "keyString": "399455s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rathas of Mahabalipuram, the rock- cut architecture, were built by a king of the dynasty of",
            "optionA": "  Chola ",
            "optionB": "  Hoysala ",
            "optionC": "  Pallava ",
            "optionD": "  Rashtrakuta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe five structures each chiselled in the shape of rathas or chariots out of large block of stone or monolith of granite typifies monolithic Indian rock-cut architecture that dates back to the 7th century during the reign of the Pallava dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "399489s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahabhasya was written by",
            "optionA": "  Gargi ",
            "optionB": "  Manu ",
            "optionC": "  Bana ",
            "optionD": "  Patanjali ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPatanjali is an incarnation of Adishesha who was blessed by Lord Shiva enabling him to write Mahabhashya. Pata\u00f1jali is one of the three most famous Sanskrit grammarians of ancient India. ",
            "keyString": "399505s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Ancient Indian literature deals with concepts about origin of universe, death and birth, material and spiritual world?",
            "optionA": "  Rig Vedas ",
            "optionB": "  AtharvaVedas ",
            "optionC": "  Aryankas ",
            "optionD": "  Upanishad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUpanishads- deals with concepts about origin of universe, death and birth, material and spiritual world, which are written in poetry and prose, as expressions of philosophical concepts. Earliest Upanishads are Brihad-Aryanaka and Chanddogya. They explain the highest thoughts described that can be realised by a man, according to ancient sages, in simple and beautiful imagery. ",
            "keyString": "399517s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was probably the most popular assembly in which even women enjoyed an equal status with men in the Early Vedic period?",
            "optionA": "  Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Samiti ",
            "optionC": "  Gana ",
            "optionD": "  Vidatha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVidatha appears for 122 times in the Rig-Veda and seems to be the most important assembly in the Rig Vedic period. Vidatha was an assembly meant for secular, religious and military purpose. The Rig-Veda only once indicated the connection of woman with the Sabha whereas Vidatha is frequently associated with woman. Women actively participated in the deliberations with men. Vidatha was the earliest folk assembly of the Aryans, performing all kinds of functions- economic, military religious and social. ",
            "keyString": "399529s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the suitable language for source material in Ancient Times?",
            "optionA": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Pali ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmi ",
            "optionD": "  Kharoshthi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSanskrit was used as an epigraphic medium in the second century A.D. Inscriptions were also engraved in regional languages in the ninth and tenth centuries. ",
            "keyString": "499575s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Smritis? \nI. It deals with the performance of duties, customs and laws prescribed according to Dharma\nII. It is concerned mainly with the rules of the organization of the monasteries",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSmriti, (Sanskrit: \u201cRecollection\u201d) that class of Hindu sacred literature based on human memory, as distinct from the Vedas, which are considered to be Shruti (literally \u201cWhat Is Heard\u201d), or the product of divine revelation. ",
            "keyString": "502528s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements about the Rigvedic Aryans is incorrect?",
            "optionA": "  We do not find any trace of widow remarriage in the Rigvedic period ",
            "optionB": "  We have some indications of polyandry in this period ",
            "optionC": "  There are no examples of child marriage in this period ",
            "optionD": "  The practice of levirate was known ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEven Vedas speaks of Widow Remarriage for a Widow. The Rigveda contains a famous passage mentioning Sati and preventing it. To a widow who is with her husband on his funeral pyre, the text says: rise up, abandon this dead man and re-join the living. ",
            "keyString": "502653s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was worshipped during Early Vedic Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Varuna ",
            "optionB": "  Indra ",
            "optionC": "  Surya ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndra is the chief deity in the Rigveda. He is the most important deity of the sky. Armed with the thunderbolt (Vajrayudha) and rides in a chariot, he travelsevery where. In Rigveda, Agni is depicted as God of fire. Most hymns are devoted to God Agni in describing and praising him, he is often considered as supreme God the creator, the sustainer and all pervading universal spirit. Surya or the sun, often identified with Aditya, Savitr and Pusan is another important Vedic deity. He rides in an exquisitely beautiful chariot drawn by seven horses. ",
            "keyString": "503556s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the popular name of Monolithic rock shrines at Mahabalipuram?",
            "optionA": "  Rathas ",
            "optionB": "  Prasadas ",
            "optionC": "  Mathika ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhakuti ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Rathas (also known as Five Rathas or Pandava Rathas) is a monument complex at Mahabalipuram, on the Coromandel Coast of the Bay of Bengal, in the Kancheepuram district of the state of Tamil Nadu, India. Pancha Rathas is an example of monolithic Indian rock-cut architecture.These Monolith temples are the part of UNESCO World Heritage Sites. ",
            "keyString": "504987s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Kushan kings, who assumed the title \"the Lord of the Whole World\"?",
            "optionA": "  Kadphises I ",
            "optionB": "  Kadphises II ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Huvishka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVima Kadphises was a Kushan emperor from approximately 90\u2013100 CE. According to the Rabatak inscription, he was the son of Vima Takto and the father of Kanishka. He assumed the title \"the Lord of the Whole World\". ",
            "keyString": "575758s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following metals was not known during the Indus Valley Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Iron ",
            "optionB": "  Gold ",
            "optionC": "  Copper ",
            "optionD": "  Silver ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIron was not discovered by the Harappan people. Since it was a bronze age civilisation, it had made many metallurgical advances in copper and bronze, but not in Iron. ",
            "keyString": "576414s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is regarded by historians as a crucial stage in describing the progress of civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Writing ",
            "optionB": "  The discovery of fire ",
            "optionC": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionD": "  The use of internet ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Historians regarded agriculture as a crucial stage in describing the progress of civilization. ",
            "keyString": "577037s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following play is set in the ancient city of Ujjayini during the reign of the King Palaka?",
            "optionA": "  Mrcchakatika ",
            "optionB": "  Raghuvansa ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Adi Kala ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMrcchakatika, also spelled Mrcchakatika, Mrchchhakatika, Mricchakatika, or Mrichchhakatika is a ten-act Sanskrit drama attributed to Sudraka, an ancient playwright generally thought to have lived sometime between the 3rd century BC and the 5th century AD. ",
            "keyString": "577617s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the ruler of the kingdom between the rivers Jhelum and Chenab?",
            "optionA": "  Alexander the Great ",
            "optionB": "  Darius III ",
            "optionC": "  King Porus ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPorus or Poros, was an ancient Indian king whose territory spanned the region between the Hydaspes and Acesines, in the Punjab region of the Indian subcontinent. He is credited to have been a legendary warrior with exceptional skills. ",
            "keyString": "578240s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of Vikramshila Vihar?",
            "optionA": "  Dharmapala ",
            "optionB": "  Gopala ",
            "optionC": "  Nagpala ",
            "optionD": "  Mahipala ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVikramashila was founded by P\u0101la king Dharmapala in the late 8th or early 9th century. It prospered for about four centuries before it was destroyed by Bakhtiyar Khilji along with the other major centres of Buddhism in India around 1193. ",
            "keyString": "645209s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bagh painting of Gupta Empire was found in which of the following Indian states?",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Chattisgarh ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bagh Caves are a group of nine rock-cut monuments, situated among the southern slopes of the Vindhyas in Bagh town of Dhar district in Madhya Pradesh state in central India. These rock cut caves posses the most amazing paintings known to be made by ancient man. These are renowned for mural paintings by master painters of ancient India. ",
            "keyString": "645334s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which emperor wrote the play 'Nagananda' in Sanskrit language?",
            "optionA": "  Prabhakara vardhana ",
            "optionB": "  Harshavardhana ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta II ",
            "optionD": "  Bindusara ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagananda is among the most acclaimed Sanskrit dramas. Through five acts, it tells the popular story of Jimutavahana's self-sacrifice to save the Nagas. The unique characteristic of this drama is the invocation to lord Buddha in the Nandi verse, which is considered as one of the best examples of the dramatic compositions.Harshavardhana was the great scholar of Sanskrit and he had written this play.",
            "keyString": "645373s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following books is based on Astrology?",
            "optionA": "  Romak Siddhanta ",
            "optionB": "  Aryabhattiya ",
            "optionC": "  Hora Shastra ",
            "optionD": "  Brahma Siddhanta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaharishi Parasara was the first to use this term in his monumental classic \u201cBrihat Parasara Hora Shastra\u201d (BPHS) showing that this scientific basis of Astrology was at different stages of development and that the rules and principles had not been fully revealed.",
            "keyString": "645411s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Veda deals with magical hymn or charms of spell?",
            "optionA": "  Rigveda ",
            "optionB": "  Samveda ",
            "optionC": "  Atharvaveda ",
            "optionD": "  Yajurveda ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAtharvaveda the Veda of Magic formulas, it is a mixture of hymns, chants, spells, and prayers. ",
            "keyString": "645437s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following places has yielded earliest Stupa railing?",
            "optionA": "  Sanchi ",
            "optionB": "  Bharhut ",
            "optionC": "  Amaravati ",
            "optionD": "  Nagarjunkondas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSanchi Stupa, also written Sanci, is a Buddhist complex, famous for its Great Stupa, on a hilltop at Sanchi Town in Raisen District of the State of Madhya Pradesh, India. ",
            "keyString": "710118s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which empire lasted the longest among the following?",
            "optionA": "  The Palas ",
            "optionB": "  The Pratiharas ",
            "optionC": "  The Rashtrakutas ",
            "optionD": "  The Senas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRashtrakuta was a royal dynasty ruling large parts of the Indian subcontinent between the sixth and 10th centuries. ",
            "keyString": "710183s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ramcharitmanas is an epic poem written in which language ?",
            "optionA": "  Santali ",
            "optionB": "  Munda ",
            "optionC": "  Awadhi ",
            "optionD": "  Sanskrit ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ramcharitmanas is written in vernacular Awadhi language, The core of the work is considered by some to be a poetic retelling of the events of the Sanskrit epic Ramayana by Valmiki. The Valmiki Ramayana is centered on the narrative of Rama, the scion of the family tree of king Raghu of the Sun Dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "710534s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the purpose of the Indian visit of Hiuen Tsang?",
            "optionA": "  To visit the holy places connected with Buddhism ",
            "optionB": "  To amass wealth ",
            "optionC": "  To know the geography of India ",
            "optionD": "  To establish political ties with India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe primary aim of the visit of Hiuen Tsang to India was to gain knowledge of Buddhism and collect its religious texts. ",
            "keyString": "710855s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The earliest specimen of Kavya style is found in?",
            "optionA": "  Ajanta ",
            "optionB": "  Ellora ",
            "optionC": "  Kathiawar ",
            "optionD": "  Mohenjodaro ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe earliest specimen of the kavya style is found in the Junagadh inscription of Rudradaman in Kathiawar in about ad 150. From then onwards, inscriptions began to be composed in chaste Sanskrit, although the use of Prakrit in composing inscriptions continued till the fourth century and even later. ",
            "keyString": "711175s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Vedas is not a part of Vedatrayi?",
            "optionA": "  Rig Veda ",
            "optionB": "  Yajur Veda ",
            "optionC": "  Sama Veda ",
            "optionD": "  Atharva Veda ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis first three Vedas are jointly called Vedatrayi i.e. trio of Vedas. The Atharva Veda is the \"knowledge storehouse of atharv\u0101\u1e47as, the procedures for everyday life\". The text is the fourth Veda, but has been a late addition to the Vedic scriptures of Hinduism. ",
            "keyString": "768485s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Choose the correct option\nI. Dharmpala was the founder of the Pala Empire.\nII. Mihir Bhoja belongs to Pratihar dynasty.\nIII. Mihir bhoja was the devotee of Lord KRISHNA.",
            "optionA": "  Only I, II ",
            "optionB": "  Only I, III ",
            "optionC": "  Only II ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMihira Bhoja or Bhoja I was a ruler of the Gurjara-Pratihara dynasty of India. He succeeded his father Ramabhadra. Bhoja was a devotee of Vishnu and adopted the title of Adivaraha which is inscribed on some of his coins. ",
            "keyString": "768817s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of Pataliputra?",
            "optionA": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionB": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionC": "  Udayin ",
            "optionD": "  Kanishka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUdayin was a king of Magadha in ancient India. According to the Buddhist and Jain accounts, he was the son and successor of the Haryanka king Ajatashatru. Udayin laid the foundation of the city of Pataliputra at the confluence of two rivers, the Son and the Ganges. ",
            "keyString": "769028s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Taxila University was located between which two rivers?",
            "optionA": "  Indus and Jhelum ",
            "optionB": "  Jhelum and Ravi ",
            "optionC": "  Beas and Indus ",
            "optionD": "  Satluj and Indus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRiver Indus and Hydaspes, river Hydaspes is now known as river Jhelum it is a tributary of river Indus. ",
            "keyString": "769238s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bimbisara was succeeded by",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Ajatashatru ",
            "optionC": "  Vasudeva ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe is also known for his cultural achievements and was a great friend and protector of the Buddha. Bimbisara built the city of Rajagriha, famous in Buddhist writings. He was succeeded on the throne by his son Ajatashatru, who murdered his father to obtain power. ",
            "keyString": "769505s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to the invaders in ancient India which one of the following is the correct chronological order?",
            "optionA": "  Greeks-Sakas-Kushanas ",
            "optionB": "  Greeks-Kushanas-Sakas ",
            "optionC": "  Sakas-Greeks-Kushanas ",
            "optionD": "  Sakas-Kushanas-Greeks ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe invasion in ancient India was firstly done by Greeks then Sakas and then Kushanas. ",
            "keyString": "845697s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who deciphered Ashokan inscription?",
            "optionA": "  Robert Clive ",
            "optionB": "  Lady Hardinge ",
            "optionC": "  James Prinsep ",
            "optionD": "  Dalhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe inscriptions found in the central and eastern part of India were written in Magadhi Prakrit using the Brahmi script, while Prakrit using the Kharoshthi script, Greek and Aramaic were used in the northwest. These edicts were deciphered by British archaeologist and historian James Prinsep. ",
            "keyString": "845780s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct statement (s) is/are correct about Upanishad philosophy",
            "optionA": "  Indicates learning from a spiritual teacher ",
            "optionB": "  Indicates learning from best teacher ",
            "optionC": "  Indicates learning from best teacher who have morality and knowledge ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeaching- Learning, Spiritual, Physical, Intellectual, Emotional, Social, Environment and Teacher- Taught relation. The Upanishads are the cream of the Vedas. The Upanishads contain the essence of the Vedas. They are the source of the Vedanta philosophy. ",
            "keyString": "845834s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following sects was Bindusara interested?",
            "optionA": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionB": "  Jainism ",
            "optionC": "  Ajivakas ",
            "optionD": "  Lokayata ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAjivikais one of the n\u0101stika or \"heterodox\" schools of Indian philosophy.\u0100j\u012bvika philosophy reached the height of its popularity during the rule of the Mauryan emperor Bindusara, around the 4th century BCE. Bindusara had interest in it. ",
            "keyString": "845858s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is/are not correct regarding the age of Vedic Civilisation? \nI. Bal Gangadhar Tilak, on astronomical grounds, dated Rig Veda to 6000 B.C. to Harmon Jacobi, Vedic civilization flourished between 4500 B.C. and 2500 B.C. and the Samhitas were composed in the latter half of the period.\nII. Famous Sanskritist, Winternitz felt that the Rig Veda was probably composed in the third millennium B.C.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vedic Period or the Vedic Age refers to that time period when the Vedic Sanskrit texts were composed in India. ",
            "keyString": "845876s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During Karikala's rule the important Chola port was",
            "optionA": "  Calicut ",
            "optionB": "  Puhar ",
            "optionC": "  Korkai ",
            "optionD": "  Thondi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPuhar Port, was once a flourishing ancient port city known as Kaveri poompattinam, which for a while served as the capital of the Early Chola kings in Tamilakam. Puhar is located near the end point of the Kaveri river, aside the sea coast. ",
            "keyString": "945678s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahabalipuram is an important city that reveals the interest of arts of",
            "optionA": "  Pallavas ",
            "optionB": "  Cholas ",
            "optionC": "  Pandyas ",
            "optionD": "  Chalukyas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMamallapuram, or Mahabalipuram, is a town on a strip of land between the Bay of Bengal and the Great Salt Lake, in the south Indian state of Tamil Nadu. It\u2019s known for its temples and monuments built by the Pallava dynasty in the 7th and 8th centuries. Mahabalipuram was the famous port city of Pallavas between 3rd - 7th century. ",
            "keyString": "945718s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The subject matter of Ajanta Paintings pertains to",
            "optionA": "  Jainism ",
            "optionB": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionC": "  Vaishnavism ",
            "optionD": "  Shaivism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ajanta Caves are 30 (approximately) rock-cut Buddhist cave monuments which date from the 2nd century BCE to about 480 CE in Aurangabad district of Maharashtra state of India. ",
            "keyString": "945735s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The paintings in the Ajanta and Ellora caves are indicative of development of art under the",
            "optionA": "  Rashtrakutas ",
            "optionB": "  Pallavas ",
            "optionC": "  Pandyas ",
            "optionD": "  Chalukyas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ellora caves were patronized mainly by the Chalukya and the Rashtrakuta Dynasty rulers between the middle of sixth century and the eleventh century A.D. Ajanta Caves in Maharashtra are 28-30 rock-cut cave monuments created during the first century BC and 5th century AD, containing paintings and sculptures considered to be masterpieces of both Buddhist religious art and universal pictorial art. ",
            "keyString": "945750s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct regarding the Vedic literature available for reconstructing the ancient Indian history?\nI. Vedic literature, mainly the four Vedas i.e. Rig, Yajur, Sama and Atharva Vedas, are entirely in a different language, which can be called the Vedic language.\nII. The vocabulary of Vedic literature contains a wide range of meaning and at times different in grammatical usages",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term Vedic literature means the four Vedas in their Samhita and the allied literature based on or derived from the Vedas. We classify the Vedic literature into the following categories: The four Vedas i.e. the Rig, Sama, Yajur and Atharva and their Samhitas. The Brahmanas attached to each Samhita. ",
            "keyString": "945764s52m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Harihara Raya I who ruled the Vijaynagara Empire for the period 1336-1356 belonged to which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Sangama Dynasty ",
            "optionB": "  Saluva Dynasty ",
            "optionC": "  Tuluva Dynasty ",
            "optionD": "  Aravidu Dynasty ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarihara I (1336\u20131356 CE), also called Hakka and Vira Harihara I, was the founder of the Vijayanagara empire. He was Bhavana Sangama's eldest son and was founder of the Sangama dynasty, the first among the four dynasties that ruled Vijayanagara. ",
            "keyString": "18234s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tuluva Narasa who ruled the Vijaynagara Empire for the period 1491-1503 belonged to which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Sangama Dynasty ",
            "optionB": "  Saluva Dynasty ",
            "optionC": "  Tuluva Dynasty ",
            "optionD": "  Aravidu Dynasty ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis was the third dynasty to rule Vijayanagar Empire. The most famous ruler of the Vijayanagar kingdom, Krishna Deva Raya belonged to this dynasty. Tuluva Narasa Nayaka (1491-1503 AD). He was the commander of the Vijayanagar army under the rule of Saluva Narasimha Deva Raya and became the de-factor ruler of the kingdom after the death of Saluva Narasimha Deva Raya. ",
            "keyString": "18264s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous dialogue between Nachiketa and Yama is mentioned in the",
            "optionA": "  Chhandogyopanishad ",
            "optionB": "  Mundakopanishad ",
            "optionC": "  Kathopanishad ",
            "optionD": "  Kenopanishad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kathopanishad is considered as a major Upanishad (out of a total of 108), and its importance can be gauged by the fact that many of its verses are found in the Bhagavad Gita, which was composed later, around 1500 BC. ",
            "keyString": "18278s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct about South-Indian Literature?",
            "optionA": "  In Southern India, the ancient Indian writings were written in four Dravidian languages which developed their own script and literature, these are, Tamil, Telugu, Kannada,Malayalam ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil is the oldest with literature dating back to early centuries of Christian era. This developed during the three Sangams(assemblies of poets and writers) held during different times ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSouth India has a literary tradition reaching back over two thousand years. The first known literature of South India are the poetic Sangams, which were written in Tamil around two to one and a half thousand years ago. In South Indian literature and philosophy, women are considered very powerful.",
            "keyString": "18290s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many spokes are there in the Dharma Chakra of the National flag?",
            "optionA": "  22 ",
            "optionB": "  18 ",
            "optionC": "  24 ",
            "optionD": "  14 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ashoka Chakra is a depiction of the Buddhist Dharmachakra, represented with 24 spokes. It is so called because it appears on a number of edicts of Ashoka, most prominent among which is the Lion Capital of Sarnath which has been adopted as the National Emblem of the Republic of India. ",
            "keyString": "18301s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following occupied the supreme position in the Later Vedic pantheon?",
            "optionA": "  Indra ",
            "optionB": "  Prajapati ",
            "optionC": "  Agni ",
            "optionD": "  Varuna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Later Vedic period, Prajapati was the important diety occupied the supreme position. Prajapatis were elected democratically. First such elected Prajapati was Lord Vishnu, followed by Lord Br\u00e0hma and Lord Shankar. There were total 26 Prajapatis mentioned in Vedas. ",
            "keyString": "95301s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following books is not written by Harshavardhan?",
            "optionA": "  Harshacharita ",
            "optionB": "  Nagananda ",
            "optionC": "  Ratnavali ",
            "optionD": "  Priyadarshika ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Harshacharita, is the biography of Indian emperor Harsha by Banabhatta, also known as Bana, who was a Sanskrit writer of seventh-century CE India. He was the Asthana Kavi, meaning Court Poet, of Harsha. ",
            "keyString": "95565s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is known as the Napoleon of India?",
            "optionA": "  Srigupta ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta ",
            "optionC": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionD": "  Devicharangupta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSamudragupta (335-375 AD) of the Gupta dynasty is known as the Napoleon of India. Historian A V Smith called him so because of his great military conquests known from the 'Prayag Prashati' written by his courtier and poet Harisena, who also describes him as the hero of a hundred battles. ",
            "keyString": "96287s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The traces of Janapadas and Mahajanapadas are found in__________?",
            "optionA": "  Vedic text ",
            "optionB": "  Buddha text ",
            "optionC": "  Jaina text ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe location of Janapadas and Mahajanapadas was Indian sub-continent. There were 16 mahajanpadas during 600 BC to 300 B.C. As per the Vedic texts Aryan tribes were known as the Janas, which were the largest social units. The term janapada composed of janas means \u201cpeople\u201d or \u201csubject\u201d and pada \u201cfoot\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "97033s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following temples was not constructed by Chandela dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Kandariya Mahadev ",
            "optionB": "  Chaturbhuja ",
            "optionC": "  Lakshman ",
            "optionD": "  Somnath ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the traditional documents of J. Gordon Melton, the first Shiva temple built in Somnath Temple was built in the old times only. And the second temple was built in 649 CE by the King of Vallabhbhai. It is said that the Arab governor of Sindh, Al-Junaid, destroyed it in 725 CE. ",
            "keyString": "97426s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who composed the Allahabad Pillar inscription?",
            "optionA": "  Harisena ",
            "optionB": "  Mahasena ",
            "optionC": "  Veerasena ",
            "optionD": "  Vishnusena ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarisena, also Harishena or Hirisena, was a 4th-century Sanskrit poet, panegyrist, and government minister. He was an important figure in the court of the Gupta emperor, Samudragupta. His most famous poem, written c.\u2009345 CE, describes the bravery of Samudragupta and is inscribed on the Allahabad Pillar. ",
            "keyString": "171114s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The eighth-century tripartite power struggle was among which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Cholas, Rastrakutas and Yadavas ",
            "optionB": "  Chalukyas, Pallavas and Pandyas ",
            "optionC": "  Cholas, Pandyas and Chalukyas ",
            "optionD": "  Chalukyas, Pallavas and Yadavas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe struggle was between the Chalukyas, Pallavas and Pandyas. The 3 kingdoms struggled for the power in South India. They were rulers of the Tamil country. ",
            "keyString": "171353s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the ancient name of river Sutlej?",
            "optionA": "  Askini ",
            "optionB": "  Vitasta ",
            "optionC": "  Shutudri ",
            "optionD": "  Parushni ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRiver Sutlej was once known as Shutudri. It is the longest river among famous five rivers of Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "171562s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has given the treatise on the rule of the Pandyan kingdom by Pandala a daughter of Herakles?",
            "optionA": "  Megasthenes ",
            "optionB": "  Kautilya ",
            "optionC": "  Banabhatt ",
            "optionD": "  Kalidas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMegasthenes was an ancient Greek historian, diplomat and Indian ethnographer and explorer in the Hellenistic period. He described India in his book Indika. Megasthenes knew about the Pandyan dynasty around 300 BCE. He described it in his book Indika, as occupying the portion of India, which is southward and extends to the sea. He had stated that it had 365 villages, each of which was expected to meet the needs of the royal household for one day in a year. He described the queen of Pandyan Kingdom at that time, as Pandaia, as a daughter of Heracles. ",
            "keyString": "171762s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following wrote commentaries on Harshavardhana's administration and the\u00a0court life in Kannauj?",
            "optionA": "  AI-Beruni ",
            "optionB": "  Fa-Hien ",
            "optionC": "  Hiuen-Tsang ",
            "optionD": "  Ibn Batutah ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chinese traveller Hiuen Tsang visited India during the period of emperor Harsha. Harsha called a religious assembly at Kannauj to honour him. Hiuen Tsang presided over that assembly. He also participated in one of the religious assemblies called by Harsha at Prayag after that. He left India in 644 A.D. ",
            "keyString": "171963s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct pair of writer and their book",
            "optionA": "  Bhavabhuti's Utter -Ramacharita ",
            "optionB": "  Bharavi's Mricchakatika ",
            "optionC": "  Vishakhadatta's Rajdoot ",
            "optionD": "  Shudraka's Kirtarjuniya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Uttararamacharita is a Sanskrit play in 7 acts in the Nataka style by Bhavabhuti. It covers the events of the Uttara Kanda of the Valmiki Ramayana, the final years of Rama on Earth up to his ascension.",
            "keyString": "274970s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs is incorrectly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Askini - Chenab ",
            "optionB": "  Sutudri - Sutlej ",
            "optionC": "  Vipas - Jhelum ",
            "optionD": "  Parushni - Ravi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVipas and Beas is the incorrect combination. Vipas modern name is Beas.",
            "keyString": "275204s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which queen of the Kakatiya dynasty ruled over Warangal, part of modern Andhra Pradesh?",
            "optionA": "  Rudramadevi ",
            "optionB": "  Ahilyadevi ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagwati ",
            "optionD": "  Bhanumati ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRudramadevi ruled over the Kakatiya kingdom, which comprised of parts of present day Telangana and Andhra Pradesh from 1261 to 1289 (or 1295) CE. Venetian merchant and traveler Marco Polo who visited India during this period has written extensively about her rule. ",
            "keyString": "275408s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who built the famous Vaikunta Perumal temple at Kanchipuram?",
            "optionA": "  Narasimhavarman II ",
            "optionB": "  Parameswara Varman II ",
            "optionC": "   Nandivarman II ",
            "optionD": "  Aparajita Varman ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVaikunta Perumal Temple was built by Pallava King Nandivarman-II in the 8th century, he was a worshipper of Lord Vishnu. ",
            "keyString": "275605s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Kailasha temple is located in the caves of",
            "optionA": "  Ajanta ",
            "optionB": "  Ellora ",
            "optionC": "  Elephanta ",
            "optionD": "  Karle ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKailashnath Temple also known as Kailash Temple is a famous temple located in Ellora, Maharashtra, India. ",
            "keyString": "275802s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Taxila was a famous site of",
            "optionA": "  Early Vedic art ",
            "optionB": "  Mauryan art ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhara art ",
            "optionD": "  Gupta art ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhara was an ancient state, a mahajanapada, in the Peshawar basin in the northwest. Famed for its local tradition of Gandhara (Greco-Buddhist) Art. Sometimes the Peshawar Valley and Taxila were collectively referred to as Gandhara; sometimes the Swat Valley was also included. Taxila was a famous site of Gandhara art. ",
            "keyString": "341153s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs does not belong to the same category?",
            "optionA": "  Mauryas - Brihadratha ",
            "optionB": "  Satavahanas - Simuka ",
            "optionC": "  Sungas - Devabhuti ",
            "optionD": "  Kanvas - Susaraman ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Satavahanas, also referred to as the Andhras in the Puranas, were an ancient Indian dynasty based in the Deccan region. Simuka was an Indian king belonging to the Satavahana dynasty. He is mentioned as the first king in a list of royals in a Satavahana inscription at Nanaghat. In the above given option only Simuka was first king and others were last. ",
            "keyString": "341199s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ comprises the archaeological remains of a monastic and scholastic institution",
            "optionA": "  Nalanda ",
            "optionB": "  Rani ki vav ",
            "optionC": "  Hill Forts of Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Fatehpur Sikri ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNalanda was the ancient Mahavihara in Magadha (Present-day Bihar) Nalanda University. It comprises the archaeological remains of a monastic and scholastic institution dating from the 3rd century BCE to the 13th century CE. It includes stupas, shrines, viharas (residential and educational buildings) and important art works in stucco, stone and metal.",
            "keyString": "341330s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main contribution of Ishwar Chandra Vidya Sagar to education and in particular to women education are",
            "optionA": "  Break priestly monopoly of scriptural knowledge(Sanskrit) and opening to non-Brahmins ",
            "optionB": "  Charles wood dispatch on education, influenced it towards female education ",
            "optionC": "  Lady Hardinge medical college at Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth A and B. ",
            "keyString": "341446s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The building of the famous Kailasa temple at Ellora was executed under the Rashtrakuta king",
            "optionA": "  Amoghavarsha-I ",
            "optionB": "  Govinda-III ",
            "optionC": "  Indra-III ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna-I ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kailasa temple (Cave 16) is one of the 34 cave temples and monasteries known collectively as the Ellora Caves. Its construction is generally attributed to the eighth century Rashtrakuta king Krishna I ( r . c. 756 \u2013 773). ",
            "keyString": "341557s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Champa was the capital of which one of the following Mahajanapadas in Ancient India?",
            "optionA": "  Anga ",
            "optionB": "  Magadha ",
            "optionC": "  Vajji ",
            "optionD": "  Kasi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnga and other Mahajanapadas in the Post Vedic period - Anga was an ancient Indian kingdom that flourished on the eastern Indian subcontinent and one of the sixteen mahajanapadas (\"large state\"). It lay to the east of its neighbour and rival, Magadha, and was separated from it by the river Champa. ",
            "keyString": "391299s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Satavahana dynasty originated from?",
            "optionA": "  South of Arawali ",
            "optionB": "  South of Vindhya ",
            "optionC": "  South of Satpura ",
            "optionD": "  South of Satmola ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe use of the name \"Andhra\" in the Puranas has led some scholars to believe that the dynasty originated in the eastern Deccan region (the historic Andhra region, present-day Andhra Pradesh and Telangana). ",
            "keyString": "392188s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ajanta Paintings belong to the",
            "optionA": "  Harappan period ",
            "optionB": "  Mauryan period ",
            "optionC": "  Buddhist period ",
            "optionD": "  Gupta period ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAjanta paintings now in Maharashtra lies in the Western Ghats which marks the boundary of the Deccan land separating it from that of Khandesh along the valley of the river Tapti. An outstanding feature of Ajanta art is that it combines architecture, sculpture and painting in its variety of expression. ",
            "keyString": "392795s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is/are correct?\nI. In the 326 BC Alexander invaded India.\nII. Ambhi, king of Taxila\u00a0welcomed Alexander and his men\nIII. Alexander died in 332 BC",
            "optionA": "  All are correct ",
            "optionB": "  Only I, III ",
            "optionC": "  Only I, II ",
            "optionD": "  II, III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 326 B.C. the Greek army approached the frontier city of Taxila (which was situated only within ten miles of modern Rawalpindi). It was unfortunate that the king of Taxila, Ambhi, to whom the Greeks called Omphis, did not resist the invaders, but instead opened the gates of his capital to the foreigners. ",
            "keyString": "393659s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whose achievements are recorded in the Allahabad Pillar inscription?",
            "optionA": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Samudra Gupta ",
            "optionC": "  Vikramaditya ",
            "optionD": "  Skand Gupta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Allahabad pillar is an Ashoka Stambha, one of the pillars of Ashoka, an emperor of the Maurya dynasty who reigned in the 3rd century BCE. While it is one of the few extant pillars that carry his edicts, it is particularly notable for containing later inscriptions attributed to the Gupta emperor, Samudragupta (4th century CE). ",
            "keyString": "394083s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India, Ancient Iron Age is attached with",
            "optionA": "  Gray pottery ",
            "optionB": "  Black and Red Pottery ",
            "optionC": "  Ocher Coloured Pottery ",
            "optionD": "  Northern Black Polish Pottery ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Painted Grey Ware culture (PGW) is an Iron Age Indian culture of the western Gangetic plain and the Ghaggar-Hakra valley on the Indian subcontinent, lasting from roughly 1200 BCE to 600 BCE. ",
            "keyString": "456698s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka sent missionaries to",
            "optionA": "  China and Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Tibet and Ceylon ",
            "optionC": "  Tibet and China ",
            "optionD": "  Kashmir and Ceylon ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t In order to propagate the Dhamma and the teachings of the Buddha, he sent nine missionaries. Each missionary was consisting of five theories in order that the Upasampada, the Ordination Ceremony, could be performed. These missionaries may have travelled along trades that spanned from the Far East to the West. ",
            "keyString": "456921s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is the oldest dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Gupta ",
            "optionC": "  Kushan ",
            "optionD": "  Kanva ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Maurya Empire was a geographically-extensive Iron Age historical power based in Magadha and founded by Chandragupta Maurya which dominated ancient India between 321 and 187 BCE. ",
            "keyString": "457119s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following book based on the exploits of Yasovarman of Kanauj?",
            "optionA": "  Rajatarangini ",
            "optionB": "  Gaudavaho ",
            "optionC": "  Malavikagnimitram ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYashovarman was king of Kannauj in the early part of the eighth century. Vakpati wrote Gaudavaho, based on the exploits of Yasovarman of Kanauj. ",
            "keyString": "457309s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of the Kanva dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Suserman ",
            "optionB": "  Vishnusarma ",
            "optionC": "  Vasudeva ",
            "optionD": "  Vasumitra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVasudeva Kanva was the founder of the Kanva dynasty. Vasudeva Kanva was a Brahmin king. He was originally an Amatya (minister) of last Shunga ruler Devabhuti. ",
            "keyString": "457498s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following places Vardhaman attained the state of enlightenment?",
            "optionA": "  Kundagram ",
            "optionB": "  Pavapuri ",
            "optionC": "  Jrimbhik Gram ",
            "optionD": "  Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVardhaman attained the state of enlightenment at Jrimbhik Gram. ",
            "keyString": "516467s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Gupta ruler who assumed the title of Maharajadhiraja?",
            "optionA": "  Skandhgupta ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta I ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta II ",
            "optionD": "  Kumaragupta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChandragupta assumed the title Maharajadhiraja (\"king of great kings\") and issued gold coins, which suggests that he was the first imperial ruler of the dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "516690s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct regarding Ancient Indian Literature that helps in restructuring of Indian history?\nI. Ancient literature is religious in nature, and contain exaggerated mythical story without any chronology i.e., puranic and epic literature\nII.  A large number of inscriptions, coins, and local chronicles do indicate an effort towards history writing",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ancient Indian literature is mostly religious in nature. The Puranic and Epic literature are considered as history by Indians, but it contains no definite dates for events and kingdoms. The effort of history writing was shown by a large number of inscriptions, coins, and local chronicles. The principles of history are preserved in the Puranas and Epics. ",
            "keyString": "516881s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is associated with the Gupta Age of Indian History?",
            "optionA": "  Visit of Chinese pilgrim Hiuen Tsang ",
            "optionB": "  Significant contribution to Indian astronomy by Aryabhatta ",
            "optionC": "  Significant contribution to poetry and literature by Banabhatta ",
            "optionD": "  Macedonian invasion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Aryabhatta was the first of the major mathematician-astronomers from the classical age of Indian mathematics and Indian astronomy. He is the author of several treatises on mathematics and astronomy, some of which are lost. His main works are Aryabhatiya and Arya-siddhanta. ",
            "keyString": "517071s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The varnas came to be transformed into the hereditary castes during the",
            "optionA": "  Later Vedic period ",
            "optionB": "  Gupta period ",
            "optionC": "  Mauryan period ",
            "optionD": "  Vedic period ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCaste system in the Rig Vedic times was based on occupations. But in the later Vedic period it became rigid when the Brahmins influenced the society with caste system. ",
            "keyString": "517255s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following writer's book gives the detail information about the invasion of India by Alexander?",
            "optionA": "  Herodotus ",
            "optionB": "  Megasthenes ",
            "optionC": "  Arrian ",
            "optionD": "  Ptolemy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArrian of Nicomedia was a Greek historian, public servant, military commander and philosopher of the Roman period. The Anabasis of Alexander by Arrian is considered the best source on the campaigns of Alexander the Great. ",
            "keyString": "559347s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the main male God worshipped by Indus people?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Shiva ",
            "optionB": "  Vishnu ",
            "optionC": "  Brahma ",
            "optionD": "  Indra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus valley people worshiped Lord Shiva as the main male god. The erect male phallus or the male reproductive power of the god Shiva. ",
            "keyString": "559586s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The accounts of Kalinga war is depicted by",
            "optionA": "  Rock edict XIII ",
            "optionB": "  Ruminidei ",
            "optionC": "  Kalsi ",
            "optionD": "  Junagarh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is the paramount importance in understanding the Ashok\u2019s Policy of dhamma. This rock edict pleads the way of conquest which is dhamma instead of war. This is logical culmination of the thorough processes which began from the 1st rock edict. ",
            "keyString": "560222s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following renowned Scholar wrote the biography of King Harsha and Kadambari?",
            "optionA": "  Bharavi ",
            "optionB": "  Bhartrihari ",
            "optionC": "  Bana ",
            "optionD": "  Magha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBana\u2019s biography of Harsha provides valuable information about the period, though with some obvious exaggeration in the emperor\u2019s favour. Written in the ornate kavya style, involving extremely lengthy constructions, elaborate descriptions, and poetic devices, the work has great vitality and a wealth of keenly observed detail. His second great work, the prose romance Kadambari, is named for the heroine of the novel. The book describes the affairs of two sets of lovers through a series of incarnations. Both works were left unfinished; the second was completed by the author\u2019s son, Bhusanabhatta. ",
            "keyString": "560490s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What led to the end of Indus Valley Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Invasion of Aryans ",
            "optionB": "  Recurrent Floods ",
            "optionC": "  Earthquakes ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe natural factors could be geological and climatic. It is believed that the Indus Valley region experienced several tectonic disturbances which caused earthquakes. These upheavals not only disturbed their life but also changed courses of rivers or dried them up. The modern satellite imagery confirms dramatic shifts in the river courses, which might have caused great flood cutting the food producing areas from urban centres. This is evident from the quantities of silt layers in the upper levels of Mohenjo Daro indicating heavy floods. Another natural reason might be changes in patterns of rainfall. During the mature Harappan age in 2500 BC, there was a great rise in the amount of rainfall, but by the beginning of the second millennium BC it had dropped dramatically thus affecting food production adversely. With the rivers shifting their courses, the rainfall declining and sufficient food failing to arrive from the countryside, there was a slow but inevitable collapse of the Indus System. ",
            "keyString": "560714s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Badami rock inscription of Pulakesin-I is dated in Saka Year 465. If the same work to be dated in Vikram Samvat, the year would be",
            "optionA": "  601 ",
            "optionB": "  300 ",
            "optionC": "  330 ",
            "optionD": "  407 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIfwe want to convert Badami rock inscription of Pulakesin I to Vikram era, it will be 465 + 78 + 58 = 601 Vikram Samvat. ",
            "keyString": "654702s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Banabhatta, a great scholar, lived during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Harsha ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragupta II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBanabhatta was a 7th-century Sanskrit prose writer and poet of India. He was the Asthana Kavi in the court of King Harsha Vardhana, who reigned c. 606\u2013647 CE in north India first from Sthanvishvara, and later Kannauj. ",
            "keyString": "654739s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which rulers built the Ellora temples?",
            "optionA": "  Chalukya ",
            "optionB": "  Sunga ",
            "optionC": "  Rashtrakuta ",
            "optionD": "  Pallava ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kailasa temple (Cave 16) is one of the 34 cave temples and monasteries known collectively as the Ellora Caves. Its construction is generally attributed to the eighth century Rashtrakuta king Krishna I. ",
            "keyString": "654755s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not have a Stupa?",
            "optionA": "  Ranchi ",
            "optionB": "  Sanchi ",
            "optionC": "  Barhut ",
            "optionD": "  Dhamek ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRanchi does not have a Stupa. Sanchi Stupa- Madhya Pradesh oldest stone structure of India. Barhut Stupa-Madhya Pradesh, its railings are the earliest railings whichhave survived.Dhamekh Stupa-Sarnath (U.P.) it is where Buddha preached the Dharmachakrapravartana for the first time. ",
            "keyString": "654769s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is not a correct pair?",
            "optionA": "  Ellora Caves \u2013 Rastrakuta Rulers ",
            "optionB": "  Mahabalipuram \u2013 Pallava ",
            "optionC": "  Rulers Khajuraho \u2013 Chandellas ",
            "optionD": "  Elephanta Caves \u2013 Mauyra Era ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tElephanta Caves \u2013 Mauyra Era ",
            "keyString": "654783s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): The Kushanas issued a large number of gold coins.\nReason (R): The period was marked by flourishing trade",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first two Kushana kings, Kujula and Vima issued gold coins. The coins were die-struck and produced in large numbers to facilitate growing trade and commerce. Largest number of copper coins was issued by the Kushanas. It was also a period of great wealth marked by extensive mercantile activities. ",
            "keyString": "714759s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote the famous Kural which in verse deals with many aspects of life and religion?",
            "optionA": "  Bhartrihari ",
            "optionB": "  Bana ",
            "optionC": "  Magha ",
            "optionD": "  Thiruvalluvar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThiruvalluvar, also known as Valluvar, was a celebrated Tamil poet and philosopher. He is best known for authoring Thirukku\u1e5ba\u1e37, a collection of couplets on ethics, political and economical matters, and love. The text is considered as one of the finest works of the Tamil literature. ",
            "keyString": "714806s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following wrote the Kural, which deals with many aspects of life and religion?",
            "optionA": "  Thiruvalluvar ",
            "optionB": "  Ayaikar ",
            "optionC": "  Shankracharya ",
            "optionD": "  Rishi Agasta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThiruvalluvar, also known as Valluvar, was a celebrated Tamil poet and philosopher. He is best known for authoring Thirukku\u1e5ba\u1e37, a collection of couplets on ethics, political and economical matters, and love. The text is considered as one of the finest works of the Tamil literature. ",
            "keyString": "714828s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Gupta emperors is represented his coins as playing the lute or Veena?",
            "optionA": "  Chandragupta-I ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta-II ",
            "optionC": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionD": "  Skandagupta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSamudragupta was a ruler of the Gupta Empire of present-day India. As a son of the Gupta emperor Chandragupta I and the Licchavi princess Kumaradevi, he greatly expanded his dynasty's political power. Samudragupta is represented on his coins playing the lute (Vina). ",
            "keyString": "714848s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The system of philosophy with which the name of Kapila is prominently associated is",
            "optionA": "  Purva Mimamsa ",
            "optionB": "  Samkhya ",
            "optionC": "  Nyaya ",
            "optionD": "  Uttara Mimamsa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSage Kapila is traditionally credited as a founder of the Samkhya school. However, it is unclear in which century of 1st millennium BCE Kapila lived. Kapila appears in Rigveda, but context suggests that the word means \"reddish-brown color\". ",
            "keyString": "714865s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which ancient account describes the Nandas expedition over all their rival monarchs that make them powerful rulers of North India?",
            "optionA": "  Manusmriti ",
            "optionB": "  Vedas ",
            "optionC": "  Puranas ",
            "optionD": "  Brahamanas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahapadma, a Shudra, who has been described in the Puranas as \"the destroyer of all the Kshatriyas\", defeated many other kingdoms, including the Panchalas, Kasis, Haihayas, Kalingas, Asmakas, Kurus, Maithilas, Surasenas and the Vitihotras. He expanded his territory south of the Vindhya Range into the Deccan Plateau. The Nandas, who usurped the throne of the Shishunaga dynasty c. 345 BCE, were thought to be of lowly origin. Mahapadma Nanda was said in the Puranas to be the son of Mahanandin and a Shudra mother. ",
            "keyString": "766390s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are poetry and drama?",
            "optionA": "  Kumarasambhava ",
            "optionB": "  Raghuvamsa ",
            "optionC": "  Abhijnanashakuntalam ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKumarasambhava, Raghuvamsa and Abhijnanashakuntalam all the three are poems. ",
            "keyString": "766438s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a religious text?",
            "optionA": "  Rigveda ",
            "optionB": "  Sangam ",
            "optionC": "  Upanishad ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sangam texts are different from the Vedic texts, particularly the Rig Veda. They do not constitute religious literature. The short and long poems were composed by numerous poets in praiseof various heroes and heroinesand are in secular nature. They are not primitive songs, but literature of high quality. ",
            "keyString": "766459s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is related to Etymology?",
            "optionA": "  Shiksha ",
            "optionB": "  Kalpa ",
            "optionC": "  Nirukta ",
            "optionD": "  Vyakaran ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNirukta means explanation or interpretation. It is related to one of the six ancient Vedangas. Nirukta mainly works on Etymology and deals with the correct interpretation of Sanskrit words in the Vedas. ",
            "keyString": "766476s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Virupaksha Temple was built by the",
            "optionA": "  Chalukyas ",
            "optionB": "  Pallavas ",
            "optionC": "  Kakatiyas ",
            "optionD": "  Satavahans ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Virupaksha Temple is located in Hampi near Bangalore, in the state of Karnataka in southern India. Virupaksha is a form of Shiva and has other temples dedicated to him. The temple's history is uninterrupted from about the 7th century when it was built by the Chalukyas. Evidence indicates there were additions made to the temple in the late Chalukyan and Hoysala periods, though most of the temple buildings are attributed to the Vijayanagar period.",
            "keyString": "766492s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the correct chronological sequence of the under mentioned Pallava kings? \nI. Nandivarman II\nII. Mahendravarman I\nIII. Narasimhavarman I\nIV. Simhavishnu",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III, IV ",
            "optionB": "  IV, II, III, I ",
            "optionC": "  III, I, IV, II ",
            "optionD": "  II, III, I, IV ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSimhavishnu (575-600 CE), Mahendravarman (600\u2013630 CE), Narasimhavarman (c. 630 \u2013 c. 668 AD), Nandivarman (730 AD \u2013795 AD). ",
            "keyString": "838229s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which inscription mentions about the village administration under the Cholas?",
            "optionA": "  Junagarh ",
            "optionB": "  Uttaramerur ",
            "optionC": "  Aihole ",
            "optionD": "  Nasik ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Uthiramerur is a panchayat town in Kancheepuram district in the Indian state of Tamil Nadu. It is noted for its temple inscriptions that describe a self-governance system existing around 7th to 9th century CE. ",
            "keyString": "838452s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Indian literature is a collection of 1028 hymns written in Vedic Sanskrit?",
            "optionA": "  Rig Vedas ",
            "optionB": "  Sama Vedas ",
            "optionC": "  Brahamans ",
            "optionD": "  Aryankas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rigveda Samhita is the oldest extant Indic text. It is a collection of 1,028 Vedic Sanskrit hymns and 10,600 verses in all, organized into ten books (Sanskrit: mandalas). The hymns are dedicated to Rigvedic deities. ",
            "keyString": "838642s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The art style which combines Indian and Greek features is called",
            "optionA": "  Sikhara ",
            "optionB": "  Verna ",
            "optionC": "  Nagara ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhara ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhara art, style of Buddhist visual art that developed in what is now northwestern Pakistan and eastern Afghanistan between the 1st century bce and the 7th century ce. ... The Gandhara region had long been a crossroads of cultural influences.",
            "keyString": "839355s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first elaborate description of Upanayana Sanskar is found in the",
            "optionA": "  Aitareya Brahmana ",
            "optionB": "  Taittiriya Brahmana ",
            "optionC": "  Tandyamaha Brahmana ",
            "optionD": "  Shatapatha Brahmana ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTandya Mahabrahmana or Panchavimsa Brahmana belongs to both Kauthuma and Ranayaniya Shakha of the Samaveda. It is consisting of twenty-five prapathakas and 347 khandas. Tandya Brahmana describes about Jyotishtoma, Ukthya, Atiratra, Prakrtis of ekahas and ahinas, Somaprayaschittas, Dvadashaha rite, collection of Yajus and Vistutis. It is famous for ancient legends. According to Samavidhana Brahmana, this work is ascribed to Acharya Tandi. ",
            "keyString": "839820s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is true about Lothal - ancient site?\nI. Lothal was an ancient port of Indus civilization.\nII. It was excavated by the S. R. Rao.\nIII. Currently it is situated in the Pakistan.",
            "optionA": "  Only I , II ",
            "optionB": "  Only I, III ",
            "optionC": "  II, III ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAncient port Lothal, India. Lothal was originally the site for the lustrous Red Ware culture, associated with the post-Rigvedic Vedic civilization.It was first excavated in 1957 by S R Rao. ",
            "keyString": "910483s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following literatures is known as Apaurusheya?",
            "optionA": "  Vedas ",
            "optionB": "  Brahman ",
            "optionC": "  Upanishad ",
            "optionD": "  Aranyak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tApaurusheya shabda (\"impersonal words, authorless\") is an extension of apaurusheya which refers to the Vedas and numerous other texts in Hinduism. Apaurusheya is a central concept in the Vedanta and Mimamsa schools of Hindu philosophy. ",
            "keyString": "911438s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gupta Empire declined in the fifth century A. D. as a consequence of",
            "optionA": "  Chalukya raids ",
            "optionB": "  Greek invasion ",
            "optionC": "  Hun invasion ",
            "optionD": "  Pallava raids ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tForeign invasions was the second major factor in the decline and disappearance of the Gutpas. The invasion of barbaric tribe Pushyamitra was not the decisive. A far more important invasion was that of the White Huns, who, after settling in the Oxus vally, invaded India. First appeared during the reign of Budhagupta. Again they reappeared under the command of Toramana who annexed a large portion of the north-western region including parts of Moder U.P. He followed by hisson, Mihirakula, who became the overlord of north India. Indeed he was defeated by Yashodharman of Malwa but the repercussions of these invasions were disastrous for the Gupta Empire.",
            "keyString": "911724s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Kushan Emperors was the first to introduce the gold coinage in India?",
            "optionA": "  Vima Kadphises ",
            "optionB": "  Vima Taktu ",
            "optionC": "  Vasishka ",
            "optionD": "  Kujula Kadphises ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVima Kadphises added to the Kushan territory by his conquests in Afghanistan and north-west Pakistan. He issued an extensive series of coins and inscriptions. He was the first to introduce gold coinage in India, in addition to the existing copper and silver coinage. ",
            "keyString": "911842s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Gupta rulers faced invasion of Hunas?",
            "optionA": "  Budhagupta ",
            "optionB": "  Kumaragupta-I ",
            "optionC": "  Kumaragupta-II ",
            "optionD": "  Skandagupta ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Huna invasion, found in Bhitari village of Ghazipur district of Uttar Pradesh, is a Gupta era pillar with an inscription dating to the reign of Gupta ruler Skandagupta (c.\u2009455 \u2013 c.\u2009467 CE). ",
            "keyString": "911952s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (S) is/are correct related to the Ancient Indian Literature?\nI. Vedas, Puranas, Kautilya's Arthashastra, and other literature besides foreign accounts are only available literary sources that restructure the Ancient Indian History.\nII. The archaeological sources like epigraphic, numismatic and architectural remains besides archaeological explorations and excavations also help in restructuring Ancient Indian History.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKautilya\u2019s Arthashastra, a book on statecraft was written in the Mauryan period not in Gupta period. The text is divided into 15 chapters known as books. Different books deal with different subject matter concerning polity, economy and society. It appears that even before the final version of Arthashastra was written in the fourth century B.C. by Kautilya, there appeared a tradition of writing on and teaching of statecrafts because Kautilya acknowledges his debt to his predecessors in the field. ",
            "keyString": "965378s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following famous ruler is called as 'Father of Inscriptions'?",
            "optionA": "  Samudra Gupta ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionD": "  Kanishka ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSamudragupta performed the Ashvamedha sacrifice to prove his imperial sovereignty, and according to his coins, remained undefeated. His gold coins and inscriptions suggest that he was an accomplished poet, and also played music. His expansionist policy was continued by his son Chandragupta II. Samudra Gupta is known as father of Inscriptions. ",
            "keyString": "965612s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of the Satavahana dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Sri Satakarni ",
            "optionB": "  Simuka ",
            "optionC": "  Pulumayi-I ",
            "optionD": "  Yajnasri Satakarni ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSimuka was the founder of the Satavahana Dynasty and he is believed to have destroyed the Shunga Power. He did so with the aid of the Rathikas and Bhojakas. He reigned for around 23 years and was beheaded by his brother Kanha, who succeeded him. ",
            "keyString": "965811s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the Muslim Invader who destroyed Nalanda University?",
            "optionA": "  Allaudin Khalji ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammad Bin Tuglaq ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad Bin Bakhtiyar ",
            "optionD": "  Muhammad Bin Qasim ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNalanda was very likely ransacked and destroyed by an army of the Mamluk Dynasty of the Delhi Sultanate under Bakhtiyar Khilji in c. 1200 CE. Muhammad bin Bakhtiyar Khalji was the military general of Qutb-ud-Din Aibak. He burned Nalanda University and Vikramshila University in 1193. ",
            "keyString": "966000s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the reign of which dynasty was the Great\nWall of China constructed?",
            "optionA": "  Sung ",
            "optionB": "  Tang ",
            "optionC": "  Han ",
            "optionD": "  Chin ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe history of the Great Wall of China began when fortifications built by various states during the Spring and Autumn (771\u2013476 BC) and the Warring States periods (475\u2013221 BC) were connected by the first emperor of China, Qin Shi Huang, to protect his newly founded Qin dynasty (221\u2013206 BC) against incursions by nomads from Inner Asia. The Great Wall of China was built during the reign of the China (Qin) Dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "966187s53m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had written the 'Rajatarangini' which was the metrical legendary and historical chronicle of the north-western Indian subcontinent?",
            "optionA": "  Megasthenese ",
            "optionB": "  Kalhana ",
            "optionC": "  Al-Biruni ",
            "optionD": "  Herodotus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajatarangini is a metrical legendary and historical chronicle of the north-western Indian subcontinent, particularly the kings of Kashmir. It was written in Sanskrit by Kashmiri historian Kalhana in the 12th century CE. ",
            "keyString": "10939s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kalinga was situated between?",
            "optionA": "  Godavari & Krishna ",
            "optionB": "  Mahanadi & Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi & Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna & Kaveri ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKalinga is a historical region of India. It is generally defined as the eastern coastal region between the Mahanadi and the Godavari rivers, although its boundaries have fluctuated with the territory of its rulers. The core territory of Kalinga now encompasses a large part of Odisha and northern part of Andhra Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "11450s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kanishka ruled from?",
            "optionA": "  Purushpur ",
            "optionB": "  Alipur ",
            "optionC": "  Indraprastha ",
            "optionD": "  Prayag ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanishka came to rule an empire in Bactria extending from Turfan in the Tarim Basin to Pataliputra on the Gangetic plain. The main capital of his empire was located at Puru\u1e63apura in Gandhara, with another major capital at Kapisa. ",
            "keyString": "11730s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indian astronomer to calculate the time taken by earth to orbit the sun?",
            "optionA": "  Aryabhatta ",
            "optionB": "  Ved Bhatnagara ",
            "optionC": "  Bhaskaracharya ",
            "optionD": "  Bishu devtampi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhaskaracharya, was an Indian mathematician and astronomer. He was born in Bijapur in Karnataka. Bhaskara and his works represent a significant contribution to mathematical and astronomical knowledge in the 12th century. ",
            "keyString": "11931s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Odisha's World famous Konark Sun Temple was built by",
            "optionA": "  Krishnadev Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta ",
            "optionD": "  Narasimhadeva ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Langula' Narasingha Deva I was a powerful monarch and warrior of the Eastern Ganga Dynasty of early medieval Odisha who reigned c. 1238\u20131264. Konark Sun temple was built by King Narsimha deva of Eastern Ganga Dynasty. It is situated at Konark, Orissa. It is part of UNESCO world Heritage site. ",
            "keyString": "12121s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following inscriptions is found in purest Sanskrit?",
            "optionA": "  Ruminidei ",
            "optionB": "  Junagarh ",
            "optionC": "  Kalsi ",
            "optionD": "  Patliputra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Junagadh rock inscription also highlights an eulogy-style Sanskrit from the 2nd-century. It is the first long inscription in fairly standard Sanskrit that has survived into the modern era. According to Salomon, the inscription \"represents a turning point in the history of epigraphic Sanskrit. ",
            "keyString": "64929s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who started the Saka Era and when?",
            "optionA": "  Kadphises in 58 BC ",
            "optionB": "  Rudradaman-I in 78 AD ",
            "optionC": "  Vikramaditya in 58 BC ",
            "optionD": "  Kanishka in 78 AD ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Saka Era was founded by Kanishka, the emperor of Kushana empire from the year 78 A.D. ",
            "keyString": "64980s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A Janapadin was the __________ of a janapada.",
            "optionA": "  Servant ",
            "optionB": "  Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Army General ",
            "optionD": "  Ruler ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Janapadin was the ruler of a janapada. Ancient texts like Ashtadhyayi, Ramayana, Mahabharatha, and numerous puranas refer to many Janapadas of ancient times. ",
            "keyString": "65264s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dholavira is situated at the bank of River",
            "optionA": "  Indus ",
            "optionB": "  Ravi ",
            "optionC": "  Luni ",
            "optionD": "  Ghaggar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDholavira is an archaeological site at Khadirbet in Bhachau Taluka of Kutch District, in the state of Gujarat in western India. It is situated at the bank of river Luni. ",
            "keyString": "65294s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of inscription is called",
            "optionA": "  Archaeology ",
            "optionB": "  Numismatic ",
            "optionC": "  Epigraphy ",
            "optionD": "  Palaeography ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEpigraphy is the study of inscriptions or epigraphs as writing; it is the science of identifying graphemes, clarifying their meanings, classifying their uses according to dates and cultural contexts, and drawing conclusions about the writing and the writers. ",
            "keyString": "65425s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is representative of Dravida style of temple architecture?",
            "optionA": "  Viman ",
            "optionB": "  Shikhara ",
            "optionC": "  Mandapa ",
            "optionD": "  Gopuram ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVimana is the structure over the garbhagriha or inner sanctum in the Hindu temples of South India and Odisha in East India. In typical temples of Odisha using the Kalinga style of architecture. A typical Hindu temple in Dravidian style have gopurams in the four directions. ",
            "keyString": "131412s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following works deals with the history of Kashmir?",
            "optionA": "  Gaudavaho ",
            "optionB": "  Harshacharita ",
            "optionC": "  Rajatarangini ",
            "optionD": "  Vikramankadevacharita ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajatarangini is a metrical legendary and historical chronicle of the north-western Indian subcontinent, particularly the kings of Kashmir. It was written in Sanskrit by Kashmiri historian Kalhana in the 12th century CE. The work consists of 7826 verses, which are divided into eight books called Tarangas. ",
            "keyString": "131657s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established Nalanda Mahavihara ?",
            "optionA": "  Kumaragupta ",
            "optionB": "  Skandagupta ",
            "optionC": "  Devgupta ",
            "optionD": "  Vedgupta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was established in 1951 under Rajendra Prasad to revive the ancient seat of learning in Nalanda. It became a Deemed university in 2006. Nava Nalanda Mahavihara was founded to develop as a centre of higher studies in Pali and Buddhism along the lines of ancient Nalanda Mahavihara. ",
            "keyString": "131788s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was the capital of Surasena Mahajanapada?",
            "optionA": "  Viratnagar ",
            "optionB": "  Junagarh ",
            "optionC": "  Mathura ",
            "optionD": "  Kashi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSurasena and other Mahajanapadas in the Post Vedic period. Kingdom of Surasena (or Sourasena) was an ancient Indian region corresponding to the present-day Braj region in Uttar Pradesh, with Mathura as its capital city. ",
            "keyString": "131906s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is a work of Tamil Grammar that is said to be the earliest extant work of Tamil Literature?",
            "optionA": "  Tolkappiyam ",
            "optionB": "  Patinenmelkanakku ",
            "optionC": "  Patinenkilkanakku ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe oldest 'extant' Tamil literature is Tholkaapiyam. It is a grammar treatise. Tholkaapiyam is variously dated by scholars from 100 CE to as far back as 500 BC (a few even stretch it back upto 1000 or 5000 BC, but those claims cannot be established solidly!) ",
            "keyString": "132018s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the last great ruler of Gupta dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Skandagupta ",
            "optionB": "  Kumaragupta I ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta Ii ",
            "optionD": "  None Of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSkandagupta, son and successor of Kumaragupta I is generally considered to be the last of the great Gupta rulers. He assumed the titles of Vikramaditya and Kramaditya. ",
            "keyString": "199684s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is not correct",
            "optionA": "  The capital of pandyas was Madurai ",
            "optionB": "  The capital of Cheras was Vanchi ",
            "optionC": "  The capital of the Videha Kingdom was Mithila ",
            "optionD": "  The capital of Gahadwal Dynasty was Kannauj ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe capital of the Videha Kingdom was Mithila. ",
            "keyString": "199777s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): The Gupta period is often called the 'Golden Age' of ancient India. Reason (R): The Gupta rulers issued gold coins",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe era between the 3rd century and 6th century CE of ancient India during the Gupta Empire can be truly defined as the 'Golden Age of India', as there was peace, development and prosperity in the country then. During the rule of the Gupta Empire, India had made lots of contribution in various sectors. ",
            "keyString": "199804s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who built Brihadeshwara Temple at Tanjore?",
            "optionA": "  Aditya Chola ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Raj Chola ",
            "optionC": "  Rajendra Chola ",
            "optionD": "  Karikala Chola ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is also known as Periya Kovil, Raja Rajeswara Temple and Rajarajeswaram. It is one of the largest temples in India. Brihadeshwara is an example of Hindu architecture from South India from the Chola period. It was built by Raja (Tirupur) and emperor Raja Raja Chola I and completed in 1010 AD. ",
            "keyString": "199836s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhara Art is the combination of",
            "optionA": "  Indo Roman ",
            "optionB": "  Indo Greek ",
            "optionC": "  Indo Islamic ",
            "optionD": "  Indo China ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandh\u0101ra is noted for the distinctive Gandh\u0101ra style of Buddhist art, which developed from a merger of Greek, Syrian, Persian, and local artistic influences. This development began during the Parthian Period (50 BC \u2013 AD 75). The Gandh\u0101ran style flourished and achieved its peak during the Kushan period, from the 1st to the 5th centuries. It declined and was destroyed after the invasion of the White Huns in the 5th century. ",
            "keyString": "199859s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most famous Chera ruler was",
            "optionA": "  Udiyanjeral ",
            "optionB": "  Nedunjeraladan ",
            "optionC": "  Senguttuvan ",
            "optionD": "  Sengannan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSenguttuvan Chera, identified with Vel Kelu Kuttuvan, the Imayavaramban, and the Kadal Pirakottiya, (c. 2nd century CE as per Gajabahu-Senguttuvan synchronism) was the most renowned ruler of the Chera dynasty in ancient south India. ",
            "keyString": "252375s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vedic term vrihi stands for",
            "optionA": "  Cotton ",
            "optionB": "  Wheat ",
            "optionC": "  Rice ",
            "optionD": "  Barley ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe word dhana, which, in Bengal at least, now means paddy or rice, implies in the Rig-Veda fried barley, which was used as food and offered to the gods. There is no allusion to rice (vrihi) in the Rig-Veda. ",
            "keyString": "252411s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vikram Shila University was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Chandra Gupta Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionC": "  Dharampala ",
            "optionD": "  Pulakesin II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVikramashila was founded by P\u0101la king Dharmapala in the late 8th or early 9th century. It prospered for about four centuries before it was destroyed by Bakhtiyar Khilji along with the other major centres of Buddhism in India around 1193. ",
            "keyString": "252428s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of the Chola temples were dedicated to",
            "optionA": "  Ganesh ",
            "optionB": "  Shiva ",
            "optionC": "  Durga ",
            "optionD": "  Vishnu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAditya I worshipped Shiva, in whose honour he built several temples. Most of the Chola Temples are dedicated to Lord Shiva. The Great living Chola Temples (Brihadesvara Temple, Temple of Garigaikorida Cholapuram and the Arivateswara Temple) were built by Cholas during 11thand 12th century are dedicated to Lord Shiva and were declare the part of UNESCO World Heritage site in 1987. ",
            "keyString": "252443s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related with the Kautilya's Arthashastra?\nI. Kautilya's Arthashastra is a book on statecraft was written in Gupta Period.\nII. Arthashastra was written in the fourth century B.C. by Kautilya, from which it appeared a tradition of writing on and teaching of statecrafts because Kautilya acknowledges his debt to his predecessors in the field",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Arthashastrais an ancient Indian treatise on statecraft, economic policy and military strategy, written in Sanskrit. Likely to be the work of several authors over centuries, Kautilya, also identified as Vishnugupta and Chanakya, is traditionally credited as the author of the text. ",
            "keyString": "252457s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The land measures of the Second Pandyan Empire was mentioned in",
            "optionA": "  Thalavaipuram Copper Plates ",
            "optionB": "  Uttirameru Inscription ",
            "optionC": "  Kudumiyammalai Inscription ",
            "optionD": "  Kasadudi Copper Plates ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Thalavaipuram copper plate, belonging to the period between 1018 and 1054 brought out by the Pandya kings, describes giant waves, most possibly a tsunami. And there is more hyperbole: the valiant Pandya kings \u201cstopped\u201d the tsunami. An earlier copper plate, the Seevaramangalam plate of 784 AD, also talks about a tsunami. ",
            "keyString": "304873s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs is NOT correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Hoyasalas : Dwarasamudra ",
            "optionB": "  Kakatiyas : Warangal ",
            "optionC": "  Pallavas : Devagiri ",
            "optionD": "  Chalukyas : Kalyani ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPallavas : Devagiri ",
            "keyString": "304909s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of following pairs is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Samaveda Samhita - Origins of Indian music ",
            "optionB": "  Atharvaveda Samhita - Origins of Indian medicine ",
            "optionC": "  Rigveda Samhita - Earliest prose ",
            "optionD": "  Yajurveda Samhita - Origins of rituals ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rigveda is the oldest and the most highly valued work of the Hindus. This Samhita (Collection) is unique in its nature. In fact, it is not a book, but a compilation composed of several books which can be individually distinguished from each other. The present from of this Samhita clearly indicates that the collection is not a single work, but consists of older and later elements. ",
            "keyString": "304928s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following cities was founded by Krishnadevaraya?",
            "optionA": "  Warangal ",
            "optionB": "  Nagalpura ",
            "optionC": "  Udayagiri ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragiri ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ruler of Tuluva dynasty, Sri Krishnadevaraya founded the town Nagalapur (near Vijayanagar) in the memory of his mother Nagala Devi and built tanks, temples, gopurams, etc. in various parts of the empire. He was known as Andhara Bhoja or Abhinav Bhoja. ",
            "keyString": "304944s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Rashtrakuta ruler built the famous Kailash temple of Shiva at Ellora?",
            "optionA": "  Dantidurga ",
            "optionB": "  Amoghvarsha-I ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna-I ",
            "optionD": "  Vatsraja ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kailasa temple (Cave 16) is one of the 34 cave temples and monasteries known collectively as the Ellora Caves. Its construction is generally attributed to the eighth century Rashtrakuta king Krishna I ( r . c. 756 \u2013 773) ",
            "keyString": "304959s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mehrauli pillar inscription belongs to the period of the",
            "optionA": "  Mauryas ",
            "optionB": "  Kushanas ",
            "optionC": "  Sungas ",
            "optionD": "  Guptas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe iron pillar of Delhi, India is a 7 meter (22 feet) high pillar in the Qutb complex which is notable for the composition of the metals used in its construction. The pillar, almost seven meters high and weighing more than six tons, was erected by Chandragupta II Vikramaditya (375 CE\u2013414 CE), (interpretation based on analysis of archer type Gupta gold coins) of the Gupta dynasty that ruled northern India 320\u2013540. ",
            "keyString": "352202s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which city of India is Dhamek Stupa located?",
            "optionA": "  Pune ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionD": "  Hyderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDhamek Stupa (also spelled Dhamekh and Dhamekha, traced to Sanskrit version Dharmarajika Stupa, which can be translated as the Stupa of the reign of Dharma) is a massive stupa located at Sarnath, 13 km away from Varanasi in the state of Uttar Pradesh, India. ",
            "keyString": "352418s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/ are correct related to the Atharva Veda?\nI. The Atharva Veda basically consists of charms and spells that were prevalent at that time in the society.\nII. The Atharva Veda presents a portrait of the Vedic society. One can find an independent and parallel stream of knowledge and thought in the Atharva Veda",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Atharvaveda Samhita contains hymns many of which were charms, magic spells and incantations meant to be pronounced by the person who seeks some benefit, or more often by a sorcerer who would say it on his or her behalf. The most frequent goal of these hymns charms and spells were long life of a loved one or recovery from some illness. In these cases, the affected would be given substances such as a plant (leaf, seed, root) and an amulet. ",
            "keyString": "352607s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the last Hindu emperor of northern India?",
            "optionA": "  Harsha ",
            "optionB": "  Pulakesin II ",
            "optionC": "  Rajyavardhana ",
            "optionD": "  Skandagupta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarsha (c. 590\u2013647 CE), also known as Harshavardhana, was an Indian emperor who ruled North India from 606 to 647 CE. He was a member of the Vardhana dynasty; and was the son of Prabhakarvardhana who defeated the Alchon Huna invaders, and the younger brother of Rajyavardhana, a king of Thanesar, present-day Haryana. ",
            "keyString": "352807s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bimbisara was the founder of which one of the following dynasties?",
            "optionA": "  Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  Haryanka ",
            "optionC": "  Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Shunga ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBimbisara was the son of Bhattiya, a chieftain. He ascended to throne at the age of 15 in 543 BC. He established the Haryanka dynasty laid the foundations of Magadha by fortification of a village, which later became the city of Pataliputra. Bimbisara's first capital was at Girivraja (identified with Rajagriha). ",
            "keyString": "352992s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following was a contemporary of Alexander the Great?",
            "optionA": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionD": "  Pushyamitra Sunga ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChandragupta Maurya (ruled 322 B.C.E. \u2013 298 B.C.E.) was the founder of the Mauryan Empire. He is widely considered to be the first great emperor of India. In 305 he successfully defeated Alexander's successors in India ",
            "keyString": "404478s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prithivyah Pratham Veer was the title of?",
            "optionA": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionB": "  Rajendra I ",
            "optionC": "  Amoghavarsha ",
            "optionD": "  Gautamiputra Shatkarni ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSamudragupta (r. c. 335/350-375 CE) was a ruler of the Gupta Empire of present-day India. As a son of the Gupta emperor Chandragupta I and the Licchavi princess Kumaradevi, he greatly expanded his dynasty's political power. He was given the title of Prithivyah Pratham Veer. ",
            "keyString": "404931s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct related to the Megasthenese profess of writing?\nI. Megasthenese wrote extensively in a book called 'Indica' which is no longer available to us.\nII. Megasthenese's writings could be seen through various extracts in the writings of Diodorous, Strabo and Arrian.\nIII. Megasthenese mentions that Indian society comprised of seven castes (jatis)",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  II and III ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndika is an account of Mauryan India by Megasthenes. The original book is now lost, but its fragments have survived in later Greek and Latin works. The earliest of these works are those by Diodorus Siculus, Strabo (Geographica), Pliny, and Arrian (Indica). ",
            "keyString": "404967s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the first grammarian of the Sanskrit language?",
            "optionA": "  Kalhana ",
            "optionB": "  Maitreyi ",
            "optionC": "  Kalidasa ",
            "optionD": "  Panini ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPanini, the first Grammarian of Sanskrit language in India, lived during the 2nd Century B. C. His famous work Ashtadhyayi has 400 sutras containing rules of phonetics and grammar. ",
            "keyString": "405205s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following built the Gomateshwara statue at Sravanabelagola ?",
            "optionA": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Kharvela ",
            "optionC": "  Amoghavarsha ",
            "optionD": "  Chamundaraya ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA monolithic statue of Bahubali referred to as \u201cGommateshvara\u201d built by the Ganga dynasty minister and commander Chamundaraya is a 60 feet (18 m) monolith and is situated above a hill in Shravanabelagola, in the Hassan district of Karnataka. It was built in the 10th century AD. ",
            "keyString": "405238s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established Mahabalipuram?",
            "optionA": "  Pallava ",
            "optionB": "  Pandya ",
            "optionC": "  Chola ",
            "optionD": "  Chalukya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe city of Mamallapuram was founded by the Pallava king Narasimhavarman I in the 7th century AD. The mandapa or pavilions and the rathas or shrines shaped as temple chariots are hewn from the granite rock face, while the famed Shore Temple, erected half a century later, is built from dressed stone. ",
            "keyString": "455517s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the author of Meghdoot?",
            "optionA": "  Shundraka ",
            "optionB": "  Vishakhadatta ",
            "optionC": "  Kalidasa ",
            "optionD": "  Chanakya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeghadoota is a lyric poem written by K\u0101lid\u0101sa, considered to be one of the greatest Sanskrit poets. ",
            "keyString": "455611s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Vedic age, who was the head of \"Grama\"?",
            "optionA": "  Kulapa ",
            "optionB": "  Gramini ",
            "optionC": "  Vispati ",
            "optionD": "  Gopati ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring Rig-Vedic era, the basic unit of power lied within a patriarchal family (Kula). The head of the family was a Kulapa. A group of such families called grama, which was controlled by a village headman Gramini. ",
            "keyString": "455972s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote Mrichhakatikam?",
            "optionA": "  Vishakhadatta ",
            "optionB": "  Vishnu Sharma ",
            "optionC": "  Kalidasa ",
            "optionD": "  Shudrak ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShudraka was an Indian king and playwright. Three Sanskrit plays are ascribed to him - Mrichchhakatika (The Little Clay Cart), Vinavasavadatta, and a bhana (short one-act monologue), Padmaprabhritaka. Mrichchhakatika (The Little Clay Cart) is a ten-act Sanskrit drama attributed to \u015a\u016bdraka, an ancient playwright generally thought to have lived sometime between the 3rd century BC and the 5th century AD and identified by the prologue as a Kshatriya king as well as a devotee of Siva who lived for 100 years.[1] The play is set in the ancient city of Ujjayini during the reign of the King P\u0101laka, near the end of the Pradyota dynasty that made up the first quarter of the fifth century BC. ",
            "keyString": "456768s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote Mudrarakshasa?",
            "optionA": "  Vishakhadatta ",
            "optionB": "  Panini ",
            "optionC": "  Patanjali ",
            "optionD": "  Shudrak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mudrarakshasa (IAST: Mudrarak\u1e63asa, The Signet of the Minister) is a Sanskrit-language play by Vishakhadatta that narrates the ascent of the king Chandragupta Maurya ( r. c. 324 \u2013 c. 297 BCE) to power in India. ",
            "keyString": "457360s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous rock-cut temple of Kailasa is at",
            "optionA": "  Ajanta ",
            "optionB": "  Badami ",
            "optionC": "  Ellora ",
            "optionD": "  Elephanta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kailasa temple (Cave 16) is one of the 34 cave temples and monasteries known collectively as the Ellora Caves. Its construction is generally attributed to the eighth century Rashtrakuta king Krishna I ( r . c. 756 \u2013 773). The temple architecture shows traces of Pallava and Chalukya styles. ",
            "keyString": "547033s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement (s) is/are correct about Ancient Indian literature?\nI. Brahmanas and Aryankas followed by philosophical doctrines of Upanishads.\nII. Brahmanas are contains detailed explanation about Vedic literature and instructions.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Brahmanas are prose texts. It describes about the meaning of Vedic hymns, their applications, and stories of their origins in details. Besides, it also explains the details about rituals and philosophies. Aranyakas and Upanishads exemplify philosophical meditations of the hermits and ascetics on soul, god, world, etc. These are partly included in the Brahmanas or attached, and partly exist as separate works. They, the Brahmanas, the Aranyakas, and the Upanishads are attached to one or the other of the four Vedas. ",
            "keyString": "547065s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which museum houses the largest collection Kushan sculptures?",
            "optionA": "  Mathura Museum ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay Museum ",
            "optionC": "  Madras Museum ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi Museum ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The Mathura Museum has a great collection of sculptures which belong to Mathura School of Art. Dating from 3rd century to 12th century. It has artifacts of the Gupta and Kushan Kingdoms as they were prominent in this region and districs of Mathura. ",
            "keyString": "547083s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On which of the following systems of Hindu Philosophy , Shankaracharya wrote commentary in 9th century AD?",
            "optionA": "  Sankhya ",
            "optionB": "  Vaisheshika ",
            "optionC": "  Yoga ",
            "optionD": "  Uttarmimansa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUttar Mimamsa is the Vedanta, one of the most significant of all Indian philosophies. As compared to other systems, its advent and growth is recent. Still it is the most influential orthodox philosophical systems of India. ",
            "keyString": "547096s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding the Aryan Economy?\nI. Aryans, crossed the nomadic stage.\nII. Lion, elephants, & Boar were not known to them.\nIII. Coins were known to them.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  II, III ",
            "optionC": "  I, III ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Aryan\" is a term that was used as a self-designation by Indo-Iranian people. The word was used by the Indic people of the Vedic period in India as an ethnic label for themselves and to refer to the noble class as well as the geographic region known as \u0100ry\u0101varta, where Indo-Aryan culture is based. ",
            "keyString": "547108s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Economy of Vedic period was based on?",
            "optionA": "  Pastureland ",
            "optionB": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionC": "  Mining ",
            "optionD": "  Cotton Cultivation ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cattle in general and cow in particular was the main medium of exchange during the Rig Vedic period. The economy was based upon agriculture. ",
            "keyString": "589457s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indian ruler who had territory outside India?",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Huvishka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanishka I, or Kanishka the Great, an emperor of the Kushan dynasty in the second century, is famous for his military, political, and spiritual achievements. Kanishka was the first Indian ruler who had territory outside India. ",
            "keyString": "589489s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the literature in Ancient India?\nI. The earliest known work of the Aryans in India was the Rig Veda which is a collection of 1048 hymns in Vedic Sanskrit.\nII. Most of the hymns are in praise of different Vedic deities and were intended for recitation at the Yajnas or sacrifices",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRig Veda Being the oldest of the Vedic literature, it is most important because it is the valuable record of ancient India. It has ten books or mandalas containing 1028 hymns by the successive generations of Rishis (sages). As the Aryans had no script of their own, the hymns of the Rig Veda were memorized and passed on orally from one generation to the other before being recorded in written form at a much later stage. It has many mantras like the Gayatri mantras which is resided by the Hindus in their houses. It is said to represent the voice of Gods. ",
            "keyString": "589503s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the longest corridor of the temple?",
            "optionA": "  Shreerangam ",
            "optionB": "  Madurai ",
            "optionC": "  Tiruchendur ",
            "optionD": "  Rameshwaram ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe temple has the longest corridor among all Hindu temples in India. The temple is located in Rameswaram considered a holy pilgrimage site for Shaivites, Vaishnavites and Smarthas. ",
            "keyString": "589518s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which king started the organization of Kumbh fair at Allahabad?",
            "optionA": "  Harshavardhana ",
            "optionB": "  Dhruvasena Ii ",
            "optionC": "  Narshimhvarman ",
            "optionD": "  Akabar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarshavardhana king started the organization of Kumbh fair at Allahabad. The Allahabad Kumbh Mela is a mela held every 12 years at Allahabad, India. The exact date is determined according to Hindu astrology: the Mela is held when Jupiter is in Taurus and the sun and the moon are in Capricorn. ",
            "keyString": "589530s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Upanishads are books on",
            "optionA": "  Politics ",
            "optionB": "  Philosophy ",
            "optionC": "  Medicine ",
            "optionD": "  Social life ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Upanishads are a part of the Vedas and are ancient Sanskrit texts that contain some of the central philosophical concepts and ideas of Hinduism, some of which are shared with Buddhism, and Jainism. The Upanishads are commonly referred to as Vedanta in the history of India. ",
            "keyString": "666339s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which ancient literature contains short stories that have the priceless treasure of morality and knowledge?",
            "optionA": "  Panchtanra ",
            "optionB": "  Hitopdesha ",
            "optionC": "  Mahabharata ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHitopadesha is an Indian text in the Sanskrit language consisting of fables with both animal and human characters. It incorporates maxims, worldly wisdom and advice on political affairs in simple, elegant language, and the work has been widely translated. Little is known about its origin. ",
            "keyString": "666710s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which script was used in Ashoka's inscriptions?",
            "optionA": "  Brahmi ",
            "optionB": "  Devanagiri ",
            "optionC": "  Gurmukhi ",
            "optionD": "  Sanskrit ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe edicts are composed in non-standardized and archaic forms of Prakrit. Prakrit inscriptions were written in Brahmi and Kharosthi scripts, which even a commoner could read and understand. The inscriptions found in the area of Pakistan are in the Kharoshthi script. Other Edicts are written in Greek or Aramaic. Most of the Ashoka's inscription are written in Magadhi language using Brahmi Script. ",
            "keyString": "666933s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following civilization is famous for its city/town planning?",
            "optionA": "  Indus Valley Civilization ",
            "optionB": "  Mesopotamian Civilization ",
            "optionC": "  Persian Civilization ",
            "optionD": "  Egyptian Civilization ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe civilization is famous for its large and well-planned cities. Over 1,052 cities and settlements have been found. Most of these are small, but amongst them are some of the largest cities of their time, especially Harappa and Mohenjo-daro. ",
            "keyString": "667130s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main focus of the Rigvedic culture was",
            "optionA": "  Indo-Gangetic Valley ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab and Delhi region ",
            "optionC": "  Indus Valley ",
            "optionD": "  Region between the Swat and the Indus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVedic culture and Indus civilization form two distinct groups in the history of Indian civilization. Of course, there are scholars like Dr A.D. Pusalkar who contend that the Rigvedic Aryans, probably, formed an important part of the populace of Indus valley and contributed their share to the evolution of that civilization. ",
            "keyString": "667323s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Iron Pillar at Mehrauli in Delhi is believed to record the achievements of",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragupta II ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe iron pillar of Delhi is a 7 m (23 ft) kirti stambha (column of fame or victory column), originally erected and dedicated as dhvaja (banner) to Hindu deity lord Vishnu in 3rd to 4th century CE by king Chandragupta II, currently standing in the Qutb complex at Mehrauli in Delhi, India. ",
            "keyString": "739701s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the most prominent god of 'Rig Veda'?",
            "optionA": "  Indra ",
            "optionB": "  Agni ",
            "optionC": "  Pashupati ",
            "optionD": "  Vishnu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are 1000 hymns in the Rigveda, most of them dedicated to specific deities. Indra, a heroic god, slayer of Vritra and destroyer of the Vala, liberator of the cows and the rivers. ",
            "keyString": "739959s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the world- famous treatise of the amorous arts?",
            "optionA": "  Kamasutra ",
            "optionB": "  Vemanasatakam ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  Neither A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kamasutra is an ancient Indian Sanskrit text on sexuality, eroticism and emotional fulfillment in life. Attributed to Vatsyayana, the Kama Sutra is neither exclusively nor predominantly a sex manual on sex positions, but written as a guide to the \"art-of-living\" well, the nature of love, finding a life partner, maintaining one's love life, and other aspects pertaining to pleasure-oriented faculties of human life. ",
            "keyString": "740271s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who constructed the Khajuraho temples?",
            "optionA": "  Halkar ",
            "optionB": "  Sindhiya ",
            "optionC": "  Bundela Rajput ",
            "optionD": "  Chandel Rajput ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The temples of Khajuraho were commissioned by the Rajput rulers of Chandella Dynasty who ruled over central India from the 10th to the 13th Century CE. The temples were built over a period of 100 years and it is believed that each Chandela ruler commissioned at least one temple in the complex during his lifetime. ",
            "keyString": "740389s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was/were the greatest poetry and drama work of Kaildas?",
            "optionA": "  Kumarasambhava ",
            "optionB": "  Raghuvamsa ",
            "optionC": "  Meghaduta ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKumarasa\u1e43bhavam is an epic poem by Kalidasa. The Kumarasa\u1e43bhavam is widely regarded as one of Kalidasa's finest works, a paradigmatic example of kavya poetry. Raghuvamsha is a Sanskrit mahakavya by the most celebrated Sanskrit poet Kalidasa. Meghaduta is a lyric poem written by K\u0101lid\u0101sa, considered to be one of the greatest Sanskrit poets.",
            "keyString": "740783s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following Indus cities has houses with doors on the main streets?",
            "optionA": "  Lothal ",
            "optionB": "  Surkotada ",
            "optionC": "  Chanhudaro ",
            "optionD": "  Banawali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLothal was one of the Indus cities that has houses with doors on the main streets. ",
            "keyString": "794021s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nagarjuna is known as the Einstein of India because",
            "optionA": "  Like Einstein he had a rare insight into the nature of the universe ",
            "optionB": "  He was one of the greatest physicists of all time ",
            "optionC": "  He propounded the theory of Shunyavada similar to Einstein's theory of Relativity ",
            "optionD": "  He was a great dialectician ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagarjuna taught the concept of relativity. He explained that shortness is only possible because of long length relative to it. He was an Ayurvedic physician (Ayurveda is a traditional Indian medicine system). Nagarjuna had been credited with explaining the circulatory system and blood tissue. ",
            "keyString": "794290s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where were the hymns of Rigveda composed?",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionC": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rig Veda is a collection of Vedic Sanskrit hymns counted among the four Hindu religious texts known as the Vedas. The Rig Veda was likely composed between roughly 1700\u20131100 BCE, making it one of the oldest texts of any Indo-Iranian language, one of the world's oldest religious texts. Its hymns were composed in Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "794538s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find the correct pair of Poet in the Court of the King during Ancient India",
            "optionA": "  Vasumitra\u00a0: Kanishka ",
            "optionB": "  Harisena\u00a0: Chandragupta II ",
            "optionC": "  Kalidasa\u00a0: Samudragupta\u00a0II ",
            "optionD": "  Banabhatta : Pulkesin II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct pair of Poet in the Court of the King during Ancient India was Vasumitra : Kanishka. ",
            "keyString": "795266s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Lingaraja Temple located?",
            "optionA": "  Madurai ",
            "optionB": "  Tiruchendur ",
            "optionC": "  Bhubaneswar ",
            "optionD": "  Ujjain ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLingaraja Temple is a Hindu temple dedicated to Shiva and is one of the oldest temples in Bhubaneswar, the capital of the East Indian state of Odisha. The temple is the most prominent landmark of Bhubaneswar city and one of the major tourist attractions of the state. ",
            "keyString": "795829s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vijaynagar ruler Krishna Dev Raya's work 'Amuktamalayada' was written in which language?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil ",
            "optionB": "  Malayalam ",
            "optionC": "  Kanada ",
            "optionD": "  Telugu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKrishnadevaraya was the king of the Vijayanagara Empire reigning between 1509\u20131530. He was the third ruler of the Tuluva Dynasty, and presided over the Vijaynagar empire at its zenith. He wrote famous book Amuktamalayada in Telugu language. He earned the title of 'Kanvada Rajya Rama Ramana, Andhra bhoj'. ",
            "keyString": "844358s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is 'Patriarchal Society'?",
            "optionA": "  System that values women more than men ",
            "optionB": "  System that values men more than women ",
            "optionC": "  System that values both men and women equally ",
            "optionD": "  System that values elders ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA patriarchal social system can be defined as a system where men are in authority over women in all aspects of society. In modern American culture and society, the idea of patriarchy is not as accepted or practiced as it once was decades ago. ",
            "keyString": "844398s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was Hampi known for?",
            "optionA": "  It was the capital of Golconda ",
            "optionB": "  It had the largest stable in medieval India ",
            "optionC": "  It had the translation of the Indian epics to Persian ",
            "optionD": "  It was the capital of Vijayanagar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt grew into one of the famed Hindu empires of South India that ruled for over 200 years. The Vijayanagara Empire built its capital around Hampi, calling it Vijayanagara. They expanded the infrastructure and temples. Modern Hampi(Karnataka) was the Capital of Vijaynagar Dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "844414s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dasavatara temple of Nagra style is located at which of the following places?",
            "optionA": "  Badrinath ",
            "optionB": "  Gorakhpur ",
            "optionC": "  Jhansi (Lalitpur) ",
            "optionD": "  Samstipur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDeogarh is a village in Lalitpur district of the Indian state of Uttar Pradesh. It is located on the right bank of Betwa River and to the west of Lalitpur hills. The Dashavatara Temple is an early 6th century Vishnu Hindu temple located at Deogarh. ",
            "keyString": "844426s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Magical charms and spells are given in which of the following Vedas?",
            "optionA": "  Rig Veda ",
            "optionB": "  Sarna Veda ",
            "optionC": "  Yajurveda Veda ",
            "optionD": "  Atharva Veda ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArtharvaveda contains mantras on three topics - gnana (Knowledge), Karma (deeds), and Upasana (invocation). It is important from the point of view of knowing the history of science in India. It is also collection of spells and charms which are popular among the people. This Veda throws light on the beliefs of the people some of the Mantras are meant to bring success in life, while some where used to ward off evil spirits responsible for disease and sufferings. This Veda believed to be a later composition and contains some non-Aryan material. It seems to have been composed when a synthesis of Aryan and non-Aryan cultures took place. ",
            "keyString": "844438s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which following statement (s) is/are correct related to the Ancient Sanskrit literature?\nI. The works of Kalidasa include the Kumarsambhava, the Raghuvamsha, the Meghaduta, the Abhijnanshakuntalam are considered classics in field of poetry and style.\nII. Bana wrote Harshacharita which is a biography of King Harsha and Kadambari.\nIII. Dandin wrote Dashakumaracharita (the tale of 10 prince)",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  I & III ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSanskrit is a language of ancient India with a history going back about 3,500 years. It is the primary liturgical language of Hinduism and the predominant language of most works of Hindu philosophy as well as some of the principal texts of Buddhism and Jainism. ",
            "keyString": "958310s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following has written Malavikagnimitram?",
            "optionA": "  Pusyamitra Sunga ",
            "optionB": "  Banabhatta ",
            "optionC": "  Kautilya ",
            "optionD": "  Kalidasa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe M\u0101lavik\u0101gnimitram is a Sanskrit play by K\u0101lid\u0101sa. It is his first play. The play tells the story of the love of Agnimitra, the Shunga Emperor at Vidisha, for the beautiful lun-maiden of his chief queen. ",
            "keyString": "958348s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the capital of Avanti?",
            "optionA": "  Gaya ",
            "optionB": "  Ujjain ",
            "optionC": "  Satna ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAvanti, kingdom of ancient India, in the territory of present Madhya Pradesh state. The area was for a time part of the historical province of Malwa. About 600 bce the Avanti capital was Mahismati (probably modern Godarpura on the Narmada River), but it was soon moved to Ujjayini (near present-day Ujjain). ",
            "keyString": "958362s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the author of Vikramakacharita?",
            "optionA": "  Ravi Kirti ",
            "optionB": "  Mangalesa ",
            "optionC": "  Bana ",
            "optionD": "  Bilhana ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBilhana was an 11th-century Kashmiri poet. He is known for his love poem, the Caurapancasika. Bilhana left his homeland in search of fame and fortune. He wandered through Mathura, Kanuj, Prayaga, Varanasi, Somnath, Kalylan and Rameswaram but luck eluded him. But while trekking back through Kalyan, Western Chalukya Empire King Vikramaditya VI appointed him as Vidyapathi. Bilhana rewarded his patron by composing in his honor an epic Vikramankadevacharita. Bilhana is from the period of time when Sanskrit continued to be the language of literature, and is a very important poet of Kashmir from the Medieval period of Indian literature. ",
            "keyString": "958374s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is incorrectly matched (in Gupta administration)?",
            "optionA": "  Bhukti - province ",
            "optionB": "  Vishya - state ",
            "optionC": "  Vithika - city ",
            "optionD": "  Gram - village ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Vishya was headed by Ayuktas or Vishyapatis. Vishya is related to district. ",
            "keyString": "958385s54m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the four varnas mentioned in the Purushasukta of the mandala X of the Rig Veda is referred in the other parts of Rig Veda in the sense of a Varna?",
            "optionA": "  Brahmanas ",
            "optionB": "  Kshatriyas ",
            "optionC": "  Vaishyas ",
            "optionD": "  Shudras ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShudra is the fourth varna, or one of the four social categories found in the texts of Hinduism. Various sources translate it into English as a caste, or alternatively as a social class. It is the lowest rank of the four varnas. ",
            "keyString": "1155s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Veda that contains charms and spells toward off evils and diseases is",
            "optionA": "  Rigveda ",
            "optionB": "  Atharvaveda ",
            "optionC": "  Samaveda ",
            "optionD": "  Yajurveda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArtharvaveda contains mantras on three topics - gnana (Knowledge), Karma (deeds), and Upasana (invocation). It is important from the point of view of knowing the history of science in India. It is also collection of spells and charms which are popular among the people. This Veda throws light on the beliefs of the people some of the Mantras are meant to bring success in life, while some where used to ward off evil spirits responsible for disease and sufferings. This Veda believed to be a later composition and contains some non-Aryan material. It seems to have been composed when a synthesis of Aryan and non-Aryan cultures took place. ",
            "keyString": "1209s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aryabhatta, believed to have been born in the 5th century AD, was a most renowned scholar of",
            "optionA": "  Astronomy ",
            "optionB": "  Biology ",
            "optionC": "  Medicine ",
            "optionD": "  Physiology ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAryabhata was the first of the major mathematician-astronomers from the classical age of Indian mathematics and Indian astronomy. ",
            "keyString": "1229s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The temple of Konark was built by Narasimha of the",
            "optionA": "  Maratha Administration ",
            "optionB": "  Chola Administration ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga Administration ",
            "optionD": "  Vijayanagar Administration ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is believed that this temple set the pace for the ratha (chariot) vimana temples in India, as a distant descendant of Kulottunga I on the female line, and the famous Eastern Ganga ruler Narasimha Deva, built the Sun Temple at Konark in the form of a chariot in the 13th century. ",
            "keyString": "1243s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Megasthenes was succeeded as ambassador by",
            "optionA": "  Darius ",
            "optionB": "  Demetrius ",
            "optionC": "  Deimachos ",
            "optionD": "  Philip ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMegasthenes was born in Asia Minor and became an ambassador of Seleucus I Nicator of the Seleucid dynasty to Chandragupta Maurya in Pataliputra, India. ... Other Greek envoys to the Indian court are known after Megasthenes: Deimachus as ambassador to Bindusara, and Dionysius, as ambassador to Ashoka. ",
            "keyString": "1257s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is/are correct?\nI. Panini's Ashtadhyayi, book on grammar in eight chapters is the final culmination of this excellent art of writing in sutra (precepts) in which every chapter is precisely interwoven.\nII. The Brahmanas elaborates vedic caste system of the society",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe system of classification, Varna is a system that existed in the Vedic Society that divided the society into four classes Brahmins (priests), Kshatriyas (warriors), Vaishyas (skilled traders, merchants), and Shudras (unskilled workers). ",
            "keyString": "142804s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chola Empire was divided into",
            "optionA": "  Mandalams, Nadu, Kurram & Valanadu ",
            "optionB": "  Mandalams, Nadu, Malkhand & Avanti ",
            "optionC": "  Mandalams, Bhoomi, Avanti &Valanadu ",
            "optionD": "  Mandalams, Nadu, Kurram & Malkhand ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe whole empire was divided into mandalams or provinces. Sometimes princes of the royal family were appointed governors of the provinces. Further they were divided into valanadus (divisions), nadus (districts) and kurrams (villages). Village was the basic unit of administration. ",
            "keyString": "144565s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is known as book of Melody?",
            "optionA": "  Rigveda ",
            "optionB": "  Samveda ",
            "optionC": "  Atharvaveda ",
            "optionD": "  Yajurveda ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Samaveda is the Veda of melodies and chants. It is an ancient Vedic Sanskrit text, and part of the scriptures of Hinduism. One of the four Vedas, it is a liturgical text which consists of 1,549 verses. All but 75 verses have been taken from the Rigveda. ",
            "keyString": "148490s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Veda, which is partly a prose work, is",
            "optionA": "  Atharvaveda ",
            "optionB": "  Samaveda ",
            "optionC": "  Yajurveda ",
            "optionD": "  Rigveda ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Yajurveda is the Veda primarily of prose mantras for worship rituals. An ancient Vedic Sanskrit text, it is a compilation of ritual offering formulas that were said by a priest while an individual performed ritual actions such as those before the yajna fire. ",
            "keyString": "149490s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which symbol shows renunciation of Gautama Buddha?",
            "optionA": "  Lotus ",
            "optionB": "  Bull ",
            "optionC": "  Elephant ",
            "optionD": "  Horse ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBodhi Tree is the symbol of nirvana of Gautama Buddha. On the other hand, Stupa represents the symbol of death of Gautama Buddha. Further, The symbol \u2018Horse\u2019 signifies the renunciation of Buddha\u2019s life. ",
            "keyString": "151242s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is a place in Larkana district of Sind province in Pakistan?",
            "optionA": "  Alamgirpur ",
            "optionB": "  Harappa ",
            "optionC": "  Rangapur ",
            "optionD": "  Mohenjo-Daro ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohenjodaro is an archaeological site in the province of Sindh, Pakistan. Built around 2500 BCE, it was one of the largest settlements of the ancient Indus Valley civilization. ",
            "keyString": "220056s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the author of Telugu Work Amuktamalyada?",
            "optionA": "  Harihara ",
            "optionB": "  Devaraya ",
            "optionC": "  Krishnadevaraya ",
            "optionD": "  Bukka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmuktamalyada is an epic poem in Telugu composed by Krishnadevaraya of the Vijayanagar Dynasty. Krishnadevaraya the great emperor of Vijaynagar Kingdom wrote 'Amuktamalyada'. (One who means or gives away garlands).",
            "keyString": "221415s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The greatest Chola king in the dynasty of the Cholas of Thanjavur was",
            "optionA": "  Parantaka ",
            "optionB": "  Rajaraja-I ",
            "optionC": "  Rajendra-I ",
            "optionD": "  Kulottunga ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajaraja Chola I and Rajendra Chola I were the greatest rulers of the Chola dynasty, extending it beyond the traditional limits of a Tamil kingdom. ",
            "keyString": "222118s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Idol of dancing girl (Bronze) is found in which of the following civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Mesopotamian Civilization ",
            "optionB": "  Indus Valley Civilization ",
            "optionC": "  Persian Civilization ",
            "optionD": "  Egyptian Civilization ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe \"Dancing girl\" found in Mohenjodaro is an artifact that echoes the architectural wonders of ancient, deep buried long ago. Some 4500 years old, this 10.8 cm long bronze statue of the dancing girl was found in 1926 from a broken down house on the \"ninth lane\" in Mohenjo-daro in Indus Valley Civilization. ",
            "keyString": "222767s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statement (s) is/are correct related to the historical literary sources of Ancient India?\nI. The 'Puranas' serves as a source of historical facts of ancient India. There are eighteen Puranas. They provide historical information of various dynasties.\nII. According to Dr. R.C. Majumdar, the war occurred in 1000 B.C. Apart from the Kurukshetra war, the Mahabharata contains various accounts of social life and religious thinking of the people of ancient India",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Puranic literature is very vast. 18 main Puranas, 18 subsidiary Puranas and a large number of other books. The Kurukshetra war described in the Mahabharata is regarded generally as a historical event. According to Dr. R.C.Majumdar, the war occurred in 1000 B.C. Apart from the Kurukshetra war, the Mahabharata contains various accounts of social life and religious thinking of the people of ancient India. ",
            "keyString": "223413s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The daughter who milks animals in the Vedic period was known as",
            "optionA": "  Kubha ",
            "optionB": "  Duhitr ",
            "optionC": "  Komi ",
            "optionD": "  Sardha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuhitri was the term used for daughter because she used to milk the cow. ",
            "keyString": "328225s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following dynasties was ruling at the time of Alexander's invasion?",
            "optionA": "  The Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  The Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  The Sunga ",
            "optionD": "  The Kanva ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNanda Dynasty ruled India at the time when Alexander, the Great was trying to fight with the rulers in the north west part of India.To be specific, the ruler was Dhannand, the last ruler of this dynasty . ",
            "keyString": "328933s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important source of our information on ancient India's cultural history are",
            "optionA": "  Archaeological excavations ",
            "optionB": "  Antiquities and monuments ",
            "optionC": "  Literature and epics ",
            "optionD": "  Inscriptions and coins ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMental and social conditions of the people are known from literary sources. The Religious Literature of India is too vast. It includes the Vedas, the Upanishads, the great epics like the Ramayana and Mahabharata, and the Puranas of the Hindus. The most important source of our information on ancient India's cultural history are Literature and epics. ",
            "keyString": "329566s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Patanjali, the second great grammarian of Ancient India, was a contemporary of",
            "optionA": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta-II ",
            "optionC": "  Gautamiputra Satakarni ",
            "optionD": "  Pushyamitra Sunga ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPushyamitra Shunga was the founder and first ruler of the Shunga Empire in East India. Pushyamitra was originally a Senapati \"General\" of the Maurya Empire. In 185 BCE he assassinated the last Mauryan Emperor, Brihadratha Maurya, during an army review, and proclaimed himself emperor. Patanjali, the second great grammarian of Ancient India, was a contemporaryPushyamitra Sunga. ",
            "keyString": "330139s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The queen with the title Didda ruled over which part of India between 980 - 1003?",
            "optionA": "  Avadh ",
            "optionB": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Sindh ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDidda (floruit 1003 CE), was the ruler of Kashmir from 958 CE to 1003 CE, first as a Regent for her son and various grandsons, and from 980 as sole ruler and monarch. Most knowledge relating to her is obtained from the Rajatarangini, a work written by Kalhana in the twelfth century.",
            "keyString": "330739s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Kailashnath Temple at Kanchi was built by",
            "optionA": "  Mahendravarman 1 ",
            "optionB": "  Narasimhavarman II ",
            "optionC": "  Nandivarman II ",
            "optionD": "  Daritivarrnan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Located in Tamil Nadu, India, it is a Hindu temple in the Dravidian architectural style. It is dedicated to the Lord Shiva, and is known for its historical importance. The temple was built from 685-705AD by a Rajasimha (Narasimhavarman II) ruler of the Pallava Dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "421374s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kailasha temple of Ellora was built by?",
            "optionA": "  Krishna I ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna II ",
            "optionC": "  Ramakrishna I ",
            "optionD": "  Ramakrishna II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKrishna I ",
            "keyString": "423560s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Panchasidhantika, written by Varahmihir is based on?",
            "optionA": "  Mathematics ",
            "optionB": "  Science ",
            "optionC": "  Astrology ",
            "optionD": "  Astronomy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVarahamihira's main work is the book Panchasiddhantika (\"[Treatise] on the Five [Astronomical] Canons\") dated ca. 575 CE gives us information about older Indian texts which are now lost. The work is a treatise on mathematical astronomy and it summarises five earlier astronomical treatises, namely the Surya Siddhanta, Romaka Siddhanta, Paulisa Siddhanta, Vasishtha Siddhanta and Paitamaha Siddhanta. ",
            "keyString": "424278s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Gupta Empire, the term \"UPARIKARA\" was used for",
            "optionA": "  An extra tax levied on all subjects ",
            "optionB": "  Periodic supplies of fruits, firewood, flowers etc ",
            "optionC": "  It was a voluntary offering by people to the king ",
            "optionD": "  King's customary share of the production normally amounting to 1/6th of the production ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUparikara was an extra tax charged over and above the land revenue. ",
            "keyString": "424807s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of following Chalcolithic sites comes under Ganges system?",
            "optionA": "  Hanumangarh ",
            "optionB": "  Alamgirpur ",
            "optionC": "  Ropar ",
            "optionD": "  Mohenjodaro ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlamgirpur is an archaeological site of the Indus Valley Civilization that thrived along Yamuna River (c. 3300\u20131300 BC) from the Harappan-Bara period, located in Meerut district, Uttar Pradesh, India. It is the easternmost site of the civilization. ",
            "keyString": "425366s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had written down the 'Ramcharita'?",
            "optionA": "  Sandhyakara Nandi ",
            "optionB": "  Chand Bardoi ",
            "optionC": "  Banabhatta ",
            "optionD": "  Kalhana ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ramacharitam is a Sanskrit epic poem written in Arya metre by Sandhyakar Nandi during Pala Empire, between approximately 1050 and 1150 CE. This work simultaneously narrates the story of the Ramayana and the Pala king Ramapala. The work is biased in favour of Ramapala, but remains an important historical source for the Pala history. ",
            "keyString": "465520s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is a treatise on the science of governance?",
            "optionA": "  Mahabharata ",
            "optionB": "  Ramayana ",
            "optionC": "  Kautilya's Arthshastra ",
            "optionD": "  Chandrawati Ramayana ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Arthashastra is an ancient Indian treatise on statecraft, economic policy and military strategy, written in Sanskrit. Likely to be the work of several authors over centuries, Kautilya, also identified as Vishnugupta and Chanakya, is traditionally credited as the author of the text. ",
            "keyString": "553402s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Ancient Indian literature was a treatise on the science of governance?",
            "optionA": "  Manusmriti ",
            "optionB": "  Arthsashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Mahabharata ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Arthashastra is an ancient Indian treatise on statecraft, economic policy and military strategy, written in Sanskrit. Likely to be the work of several authors over centuries, Kautilya, also identified as Vishnugupta and Chanakya, is traditionally credited as the author of the text. ",
            "keyString": "554124s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select correct pair of book and author",
            "optionA": "  Mudrarakshasa: Somdeva ",
            "optionB": "  Brihat Samhita: Ravi Kriti ",
            "optionC": "  Kathasaritsagar: Visakdatta ",
            "optionD": "  Panchsidhantika : Varharmihara ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVarahamihira wrote Panchasiddhantika(Five schools of Astronomy) in which he focused on three different branches of astronomy as studied during the period and they were; astronomy and mathematics, astrology ",
            "keyString": "554739s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not an important limb of Vedas?",
            "optionA": "  Siksha (Phonetics) ",
            "optionB": "  Kalpa (Ritual) ",
            "optionC": "  Vyakarna (Grammar) ",
            "optionD": "  Ashtadhyayi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPa\u1e47ini is known for his text Ashtadhyayi, a sutra-style treatise on Sanskrit grammar, 3,959 \"verses\" or rules on linguistics, syntax and semantics in \"eight chapters\" which is the foundational text of the Vy\u0101kara\u1e47a branch of the Vedanga, the auxiliary scholarly disciplines of the Vedic period. ",
            "keyString": "555315s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct about ancient Indian literature?",
            "optionA": "  The Puranas is important as they were the main influence in the development from early Vedic religion to Hinduism ",
            "optionB": "  The Shastras contained works of science and philosophy ",
            "optionC": "  The Bhagvad Gita a later addition to the Mahabharata enshrines a philosophical doctrine and in it are described the three paths to salvation: karma, gyan and bhakti ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Puranas (Sanskrit: pura\u1e47a, \"of ancient times\") are Hindu religious texts that are part of the Vedas. Shastra commonly refers to a treatise or text on a specific field of knowledge. In early Vedic literature, the word referred to any precept, rule, teaching, ritual instruction or direction. The Bhagavad Gita, often referred to as the Gita, is a 700-verse Hindu scripture in Sanskrit that is part of the Hindu epic Mahabharata. ",
            "keyString": "555880s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the four works mentioned below which one is encyclopaedic in nature?",
            "optionA": "  Amarakosha ",
            "optionB": "  Siddhanta Shiromani ",
            "optionC": "  Brihat Samhita ",
            "optionD": "  Astanga Hridaya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBrihat Samhita, another important contribution of Varahamihira is the encyclopedic Brihat-Samhita. Although the book is mostly about divination, it also includes a wide range of subjects other than divination. It covers wide ranging subjects of human interest, including astronomy, planetary movements, eclipses, rainfall, clouds, architecture, growth of crops, manufacture of perfume, matrimony, domestic relations, gems, pearls, and rituals. The volume expounds on gemstone evaluation criterion found in the Garuda Purana, and elaborates on the sacred Nine Pearls from the same text. It contains 106 chapters and is known as the \"great compilation\". ",
            "keyString": "625335s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are two works of Kalidasa?",
            "optionA": "  Raghuvamsha and Kiratarjuniya ",
            "optionB": "  Kumara Sambhav and Raghuvamsha ",
            "optionC": "  Malti Madhava and Kumara Sambhava ",
            "optionD": "  Malti Madhav and Kumara Sambhava ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kumarasa\u1e43bhavam is widely regarded as one of Kalidasa's finest works, a paradigmatic example of kavya poetry. The style of description of spring set the standard for nature metaphors pervading many centuries of Indian literary tradition.Raghuvamsha is a Sanskrit mahakavya (epic poem) by the most celebrated Sanskrit poet Kalidasa. ",
            "keyString": "626232s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pairs is correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Buddhist monastery ",
            "optionB": "  Buddhist order or organisation ",
            "optionC": "  A kind of tomb where the relics of Buddha and other Buddhist monks are kept ",
            "optionD": "  A Buddhist assembly hall or temple ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRelic stupa, in which the relics or remains of the Buddha, his disciples, and lay saints are interred. Object stupa, in which the items interred are objects belonged to the Buddha or his disciples, such as a begging bowl or robe, or important Buddhist scriptures. ",
            "keyString": "627021s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which painting is made from Fresco style?",
            "optionA": "  Bhimbetka ",
            "optionB": "  Piklikhal ",
            "optionC": "  Ajanta ",
            "optionD": "  Ellora ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe painting techniques at Ajanta are similar to European fresco technique. The primary difference is that the layer of plaster was dry when it was painted. First, a rough plaster of clay, cow dung, and rice husks were pressed on to the rough cave walls. ",
            "keyString": "629236s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was the capital of Kosala?",
            "optionA": "  Sravasti ",
            "optionB": "  Shuktimati ",
            "optionC": "  Kaushambi ",
            "optionD": "  Indraprastha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShravasti is recorded as the capital of Kosala during the Mahajanapada period (6th\u20135th centuries BCE), but post-Maurya (2nd\u20131st centuries BCE) kings issued their coins from Ayodhya. ",
            "keyString": "630356s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Greek Roman Art has found a place in",
            "optionA": "  Ellora ",
            "optionB": "  Gandhara ",
            "optionC": "  Kalinga ",
            "optionD": "  Bhuddhist Art ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhara school of art is also known as the Greek Roman school of Art. The depiction of Buddha as Man-God influenced from Greek Mythology.",
            "keyString": "709484s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For which period did Harihara Raya II of Sangma dynasty ruled the Vijaynagara Empire?",
            "optionA": "  1446-1465 ",
            "optionB": "  1485-1491 ",
            "optionC": "  1491-1505 ",
            "optionD": "  1377-1404 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vijayanagara Empire (also called Karnata Empire, and the Kingdom of Bisnegar by the Portuguese) was based in the Deccan Plateau region in South India. It was established in 1336 by Harihara I and his brother Bukka Raya I of Sangama Dynasty. It ruled from 1377-1404. ",
            "keyString": "711168s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of pottery was most popular with the Later Vedic people?",
            "optionA": "  Black-slipped Ware ",
            "optionB": "  Black and Red Ware ",
            "optionC": "  Painted Grey Ware ",
            "optionD": "  Red Ware ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe later Vedic people were acquainted with four types of pottery\u2014black-and-red ware, black- slipped ware, Painted Grey Ware, and red-ware. The last type of pottery was the most popular, and is found almost all over western UP. However, the most distinctive pottery of the period is known as Painted Grey Ware. ",
            "keyString": "711678s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All souls day is a __________ festival.",
            "optionA": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionB": "  Jainism ",
            "optionC": "  Christian ",
            "optionD": "  Muslim ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t In Christianity, All Souls' Day or the Commemoration of All the Faithful Departed, that is, of the souls of all Christians who have died, follows All Saints' Day. Observing Christians typically remember deceased relatives on the day. ",
            "keyString": "712156s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kalidasa's works include:\nI. Abhijnanashakuntalam\nII. Meghadutam\nIII. Raghuvamsa\nIV. Malvikagnimitram\nV. Ritusamhara\nVI. Kumarasambhava\nSelect the correct option",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III and IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, II, IV, V and VI ",
            "optionC": "  I, III , IV and V ",
            "optionD": "  All of them ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbhijnanasakuntalam by Kalidasa is one of the greatest dramas depicting love, separation & reunion of King Dushyanta, Sakuntala & their son (Bharata). Meghadutam is a lyric poem written by Kalidasa, considered to be one of the greatest Sanskrit poets. Raghuvamsha is a Sanskrit mahakavya by the most celebrated Sanskrit poet Kalidasa. The Malavikagnimitram is a Sanskrit play by Kalidasa. It is his first play. The play tells the story of the love of Agnimitra, the Shunga Emperor at Vidisha, for the beautiful lun-maiden of his chief queen. Rtusamhara, often written Ritusamhara, is a long poem or mini-epic in Sanskrit by Kalidasa. Kumarasambhavam is an epic poem by Kalidasa. ",
            "keyString": "712703s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The words Satyameva Jayate in the State Emblem adopted by the Government of India have been taken from which Upanishad?",
            "optionA": "  Aitareya Upanishad ",
            "optionB": "  Mundaka Upanishad ",
            "optionC": "  Adhyatma Upanishad ",
            "optionD": "  Prasna Upanishad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Truth alone triumphs\" is a mantra from the ancient Indian scripture Mundaka Upanishad. Following the independence of India, it was adopted as the national motto of India in 26 January 1950. It is inscribed in script at the base of the national emblem. ",
            "keyString": "778528s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct regarding the Dharmasutras and the Smritis? \nI. Texts were considered as the rules and regulations for the general public and for the rulers.\nII. Dharmasutras and the Smritis can also be termed in the modern concept as the constitution and law books for the ancient Indian polity and society",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDharmasastra became influential in modern colonial India history, when they were formulated by early British colonial administrators to be the law of the land for all non-Muslims (Hindus, Jains, Buddhists, Sikhs) in India, after Sharia was already accepted as the law for Muslims in colonial India. Smriti, literally \"that which is remembered\" are a body of Hindu texts usually attributed to an author, traditionally written down but constantly revised, in contrast to \u015arutis considered authorless, that were transmitted verbally across the generations and fixed. ",
            "keyString": "779223s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who established the four monasteries Sringeri, Badrinath, Dwarka & Puri?",
            "optionA": "  Ramanuj ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Shankaracharya ",
            "optionD": "  Madhav Vidhyaranya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAdi Shankaracharya wished to grace the Indian subcontinent by establishing five major mathas in the four corners of the peninsula \u2013 north (Jyothirmath), south (Sringeri,Kanchi ), east (Puri), west (Dwaraka) \u2013 to propagate the philosophy of advaita vedanta and to promulgate the concept of Sanatana dharma, thus establishing dharma or righteousness, as the way of life of people. ",
            "keyString": "779831s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was an important Port of the eastern coast during Gupta period?",
            "optionA": "  Kalyan ",
            "optionB": "  Tamralipti ",
            "optionC": "  Sopara ",
            "optionD": "  Baroch ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTamralipti was an ancient port city and also one of Buddhist Kingdoms visited by Xuanzang in 639 AD. It has been identified with the modern Tamluk in the Midnapur district, West Bengal, India. ",
            "keyString": "780403s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Indian literature is the earliest known works?",
            "optionA": "  Puranas ",
            "optionB": "  Rig Vedas ",
            "optionC": "  Sama Vedas ",
            "optionD": "  Rajtrangini ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Earliest known works of Indian literature was Rig Veda, which is a collection of 1028 hymns written in Vedic Sanskrit. Even though majority of the literary works which have survived from the ancient Indian literature are religious text, it is not right to define ancient Indian literature only based on religion. ",
            "keyString": "781241s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find out the odd one",
            "optionA": "  Hiuen-Tsang: Acquired knowledge of Indian society through literature ",
            "optionB": "  AI-Biruni: Given valuable account about Harshavardhana ",
            "optionC": "  Megasthenes: Describes about the Indo-Persian relations ",
            "optionD": "  Ptolemy: Written a geographical treatise on India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPtolemy: Written a geographical treatise on India ",
            "keyString": "845369s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?",
            "optionA": "  Sunga dynasty was founded by pushyamitra ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka the great Mauryan king died in 332 BC ",
            "optionC": "  Ashoka invaded the Kalinga in 261 BC ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragupta Maurya earned the title of the Liberator ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka, sometimes Ashoka the Great, was an Indian emperor of the Maurya Dynasty, who ruled almost all of the Indian subcontinent from c. 268 to 232 BCE. The grandson of the founder of the Maurya Dynasty, Chandragupta Maurya, Ashoka promoted the spread of Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "845948s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pairs of persons are\u00a0correctly matched?\nI. Chandragupta-II : Fa-Hien\nII. Skandagupta: I-tsing\nIII. Harsha: Hiuen Tsang",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChandragupta-II : Fa-Hien and Harsha: Hiuen Tsang are correctly matched. ",
            "keyString": "846491s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was the book written by Amoghvarsha the Rashtrakuta King?",
            "optionA": "  Adipurana ",
            "optionB": "  Ganitasara Samgraha ",
            "optionC": "  Saktayana ",
            "optionD": "  Kavirajamarg ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmoghavarsha was a scholar in Kannada and Sanskrit literature. His own writing Kavirajamarga is a landmark literary work in the Kannada language and became a guide book for future poets and scholars for centuries to come. ",
            "keyString": "847008s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct about Panini's great grammar the Ashtadhyayi?",
            "optionA": "  It was most probably composed towards the 4th century BC ",
            "optionB": "  It was stated that with Panini the language attained its highest state of development and thereafter there was improvement only in its vocabulary ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tP\u0101\u1e47ini was an ancient Sanskrit philologist, grammarian, and a revered scholar in ancient India. Considered the father of linguistics. Ashtadhyayi is the foundational text of the grammatical branch of the Vedanga, the auxiliary scholarly disciplines of Vedic religion. ",
            "keyString": "847735s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote 'Nyaya Sutra'?",
            "optionA": "  Vyasa ",
            "optionB": "  Gautam ",
            "optionC": "  Kapila ",
            "optionD": "  Charaka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Nyaya Sutra of Gotama is an important treatise on Indian logic and is regarded as the earliest work of Nyaya philosophy. Written in the aphoristic style, it is believed to have been comprised by Gotama, Gautama or Aksapada who is also considered to be the founder of the Nyaya system of philosophy. ",
            "keyString": "911217s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote Panchatantra?",
            "optionA": "  Kalidas ",
            "optionB": "  Vishnu Sharma ",
            "optionC": "  Chanakya ",
            "optionD": "  Nagarjun ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVishnu Sharma was an Indian scholar and author who is believed to have written the Panchatantra collection of fables. The exact period of the composition of the Panchatantra is uncertain, and estimates vary from 1200 BCE to 300 CE. ",
            "keyString": "913202s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote Si- Yu- ki?",
            "optionA": "  Harshavardhan ",
            "optionB": "  Selucas Nicator ",
            "optionC": "  Hieun Tsiang ",
            "optionD": "  Megasthanese ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHieun Tsiang was a Chinese Buddhist monk, scholar, traveller, and translator who travelled to India in the seventh century and described the interaction between Chinese Buddhism and Indian Buddhism during the early Tang dynasty.",
            "keyString": "913828s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Kalidasa : Kumarasambhava ",
            "optionB": "  Shudraka : Mrichchhakatika ",
            "optionC": "  Varahamihira : Brihat-samhita ",
            "optionD": "  Vishakhadatta : Kaumudi-mahotsava ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKaumudi-Mahotsava (\"Festival of Moonlight\") is a Sanskrit play of uncertain date. It is known from a single manuscript discovered in the present-day Kerala state of India. Its style and language suggest that it was composed around the 3rd century. The play narrates the story of prince Kalyanavarman of Magadha. ",
            "keyString": "914404s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not matched correctly?",
            "optionA": "  Vardhamana Mahavira's father-Siddhartha ",
            "optionB": "  Vardhamana Mahavira's mother- Trisala ",
            "optionC": "  Vardhamana Mahavira's wife-Yashoda ",
            "optionD": "  Vardhamana Mahavira's daughter-Cheiiana ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVardhamana Mahavira's daughter name was Priyadarshana ",
            "keyString": "914967s55m7h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}